If you can't see me, and also can't hear me, but can text with me, would you consider me
intelligent? What if you communicated with a computer with text messages? Would you consider
it intelligent? Let's take a look at what this has to do with artificial intelligence,
and look at how AI researchers have defined AI in the past.
To define artificial intelligence, it helps to look at what some of the early founders of computer science and AI had to say about it.
Alan Turing is considered one of the founders of theoretical computer science, and he provided the mathematical theory behind the modern-day computer.
In 1950, Turing wrote a paper in which he asked,
He proposed a way of answering that question called the imitation game, in which a human observer has conversations by text with a human,
and also has a similar conversation with a machine.
The observer cannot see or hear the other human or the machine,
so the observer has to decide purely on the quality of the text-based conversation
if the person on the other side is a human or not.
If the human cannot distinguish between the machine and the other human,
who is also communicating by text,
then that machine demonstrates the ability to think.
This imitation game is now also called the Turing Test. As a historical note, there was actually a
pretty cool movie about Alan Turing and his team's efforts during the Second World War to decrypt the
military communications of Nazi Germany. The name of the movie is The Imitation Game. The exact term
artificial intelligence was first coined by another founder of computer science, John McCarthy.
In 1952, McCarthy and other scientists met at Dartmouth College to propose a study of whether machines can be designed to simulate intelligence.
They wrote that their research would be based on the conjecture that every aspect of learning or any other feature of intelligence can in principle be so precisely described that a machine can be made to simulate it.
McCarthy formally defined artificial intelligence as the science and engineering of making intelligent
machines. But how do we define intelligence? McCarthy defined intelligence as the computational
part of the ability to achieve goals in the world. Another way to think about this is the ability to
perform useful tasks. So from a historical perspective, artificial intelligence is a field
of research that began in the 1950s with the goal of getting machines to perform tasks that require
intelligence. Let's break this down a bit. Artificial and machine means that it's not performed
by biological intelligence, like a human, a dog, or a panda. It's task-oriented. The machine is
taking some action, like outputting a number or some text, to achieve a useful outcome. The third
part is intelligence. And defining intelligence can get somewhat philosophical, but intelligence
includes the ability to make decisions even in ambiguous circumstances, and to learn from
experience. Intelligence is often defined in terms of what humans are able to do, although it doesn't
have to be limited to human intelligence. Next, let's take a closer look at defining intelligence.