Does performing this task require intelligence?
How about this?
Does this require intelligence?
Some tasks are harder than others,
so we'd say they require more intelligence.
Let's take a look at some tasks that we can do.
tasks that have different levels of difficulty to better understand what is considered intelligence.
Here is an image in a photo app. How would you instruct a computer to convert the image to
grayscale? You can apply a math formula that takes an average of the red, green, and blue to convert
it to grayscale. Since this task can be accomplished pretty consistently with some math, we wouldn't
consider this to acquire much intelligence. How about if you crop the image? If you give the machine
the exact size and shape that you want to crop, the machine can perform this task well by following
some simple rules. So this wouldn't require much intelligence. But what if you ask the machine
to choose how to crop the image? This task is more nuanced because the computer needs to figure out
what it should keep in the image and what it should leave out. For instance, it probably should keep
the person and other relevant objects inside the image after cropping. So this may require some more
intelligence to do the task well. What if you wanted the computer to identify some of the objects
in the image and tell you what they are? For instance, I'd like to identify what these round
objects are. This task is harder for a computer to do well with a few simple instructions because
there are many other objects that are round and white, and so doing a simple match based on color
or shape probably won't be enough. You could imagine all the rules you might need to give the machine
and also exceptions to those rules in order to do this task well.
So it's fair to say that this task requires more intelligence.
What if you want to make an object in the image disappear?
This eraser lets me hand draw a circle around some object,
and it cleanly removes that object.
But instead of just leaving an empty hole where the object was,
it fills in the missing space quite well with what would reasonably be behind that object.
And by the way, I was able to make that round steamed bun disappear without a photo app by eating it.
If you imagine giving a computer instructions for how to do this, it would require a lot of instructions,
and even then, you might not even be able to think of all the instructions and exceptions that are needed to perform this task well in most situations.
So this task probably requires more intelligence too.
One way to think of intelligence is the ability to perform tasks that humans do well, such as
understanding images, text, and language. And it helps to think of these as a spectrum of tasks
that may be easier or harder for a machine or even a human to do. An easier task would require
fewer rules, whereas a more difficult task would require more rules. You can think of the difficulty
of a task in terms of how many rules and exceptions to those rules you'd have to give a machine in
order for it to do the task well. To perform well on a difficult task, a person or computer would
ideally be able to handle ambiguity. This means they can handle situations that they haven't
encountered before and still achieve a reasonable outcome. In the early days of AI research,
writing these rules allowed machines to perform some useful tasks with images, text, and numbers.
But what happens when giving lots of rules and instructions just isn't enough? Coming up next,
There's another approach in AI that doesn't rely on humans to come up with these rules and instructions.
It's called machine learning.
Let's look at machine learning next.