When you're taking this course, there may be points where you feel like you're getting stuck,
and you may be wondering whether you need to keep studying that piece until you can move forward,
or maybe even go deeper in that subject before you move forward in the course.
What I'd actually recommend to you is to keep moving forward and see the whole course first,
and that way, when you see the big picture, you'll actually have a better understanding
of some of those things that you got stuck on earlier.
Let's talk a little bit more about the big picture.
When you're learning a new subject, there will be times when you feel unsure about something
and maybe feel a little bit stuck.
For example, you may still be wondering, what is AI really?
It's like if you're hiking on a trail and deciding whether to stay where you are or continue walking.
You might wonder if it's better to rewatch the video or maybe stop and think about it a little bit longer.
Another option to consider is to keep moving forward to see what comes next in your studies.
For example, while you're still pondering what AI really is, you can also learn a little bit about
computer vision, and then learn a little bit about machine translation, and then learn a lot about
chatbots. When you give yourself the permission to move forward in the rest of the curriculum,
sometimes what you learn later can help you answer some of those questions that you had earlier.
And even if that's not always the case, when you move forward in your studies,
you'll learn a lot of things that may give you more confidence when you go back to address
some of those questions that you had earlier. As you're studying a subject such as AI,
something else you'll likely encounter is that there are many other related subjects,
so there are also many possible paths you can take in your studies. Some of these topics may
be really interesting, or you may feel that these are prerequisites that you have to study first
before you can continue on your original journey. It's great to be excited about exploring on your
own, but I also suggest that you can also explore those topics later. Usually, a course is designed
to help you focus on a certain set of topics to help you learn what's most relevant for the goals
of the course. This means intentionally leaving some content out of the course in order to let you
move forward more efficiently. Specific to AI, you may learn about or get advice about learning more
math or learning coding, or you may also hear about other important topics such as data analysis or
data science. These are definitely great to learn too, at some point, but you can learn a lot about
AI and even start using AI in some daily tasks or at work, even before you get to studying those
other topics. I think that seeing the benefits of AI first can also make it more fun if and when you
do decide to get into the math and coding, or when you decide to study other useful and related topics
such as data analysis and data science. But the reason I want to suggest that you not feel required
to learn those things as your first step is that too often people get stuck or discouraged when
studying some of those prerequisites. It's a little like getting stuck on a hiking trail that is
difficult and not yet very fun. So some people may wonder if it's worth it to keep going. But if they
get to see and interact with some of the cool stuff first, this will make it easier and more motivating
to keep learning. C'est comme si vous aviez la possibilité de vous placer d'abord au sommet d'une colline pour avoir une belle vue d'ensemble.
of the whole trail, then when you return to the ground and hike through it on foot, you'll have a
better sense of where you're going and what to expect along the way, and also what to look forward
to when you reach your destination. Learning the math and coding will eventually help you if you
want to go deeper into the field, and I think it will be more motivating when you do learn those
foundational topics if you can already see the end results of all that math, code, and theory.
So please try to get that big picture view from above and check out the cool things that you can
do with AI. When you're ready, you can still revisit the topics that you covered earlier
and go deeper if you want to. Next up, you'll learn about computer vision,
starting with how to locate and identify objects in the picture.