If you want to learn how to bake a cake, how would you do that?
One way to learn is to get a cookbook and follow the instructions step by step.
Another way to do that is to watch a friend, family member, or someone on YouTube do it,
and then you can follow along and try to mimic what they're doing.
Let's see how this relates to AI, and in particular a subfield of AI called machine learning.
So going back to a little bit of history, AI researchers from the 1950s to 1980s primarily
worked on a subfield of AI called symbolic AI in which they came up with ever more complex
instructions to get machines to perform tasks intelligently. This is often referred to as a
rules-based approach. However, at the same time, there was another approach called machine learning
based on statistics, and it tried to get a computer to learn from data and examples instead of giving
it lots of rules to follow. The term of machine learning was first coined by Arthur Samuel,
a researcher at IBM, who trained a computer to play the game of checkers, not by giving it lots
of instructions on how to play the game, but by getting the computer to play checkers against a
version of itself and to learn over time what moves gave it more points or fewer points. Tom
Mitchell, a professor who founded Carnegie Mellon's machine learning department, gave a formal
definition of machine learning that's been widely cited. I'll first give one of his quotes from his
book, then the more formal and famous one. Machine learning is the study of algorithms that allows
computer programs to automatically improve through experience. And here's the original definition
from Tom Mitchell. I removed some words because I think it helps to see the simpler wording first.
A computer program is said to learn from experience with respect to some tasks if its performance
at the tasks as measured improves with experience. And now here's the full text. A program is said to
learn from experience E with respect to some class of tasks T and performance measure P if its
performance at tasks in T, as measured by P, improves with experience E. In other words,
a machine learns from experience if it performs a task, gets objective feedback on how well it does,
and then uses that feedback to get better at that task. Let's walk through an example of the
machine learning approach. Suppose you want a machine to perform a task of identifying whether
a photograph is of a panda or not a panda. You give the machine an image and ask it to output
panda or not panda. So far, it knows nothing about what pandas look like, but it performs the task
as best it can and in this case outputs not a panda. Then you give it the correct answer, panda.
The machine takes note that its prediction was incorrect and makes some adjustments.
Then you give it another image like this one. It tries its best and in this case outputs panda.
You give it the correct answer, which is also panda.
Again, the machine uses your feedback, compares it to what it output itself, and makes adjustments,
or essentially learns, so that it can do better the next time it performs the task.
So the next time it does this task again, whether on the same image or on new images that it's never seen before,
it gets better at predicting whether the image is of a panda or not.
And you do this in a loop, with many images, probably between 100 and 1000.
For each image, you provide the correct answer to the machine only after it has attempted
to do the task itself.
It predicts "not panda" and it gets the feedback that it's correct.
Here it predicts that this is a panda and it gets feedback that it's actually not a panda.
It predicts that this is a panda and it gets feedback that this is actually not a panda.
to get better at performing this task.
And one more thing, you can actually try this yourself
with something called Teachable Machine
offered by Google on this free website.
Let's take a look at how to use it.
If you go here, just click on Get Started,
click on Image Project on the left,
and then for this pop-up, just choose the one on the left,
Standard Image Model.
And here you can see that it lets you take pictures
of one class of objects and a second class of objects.
I'm going to use Pandas for the first class
and dogs for the second.
So let me just change the label to Panda on the top
and Dog on the bottom.
And then for the Panda, I'm going to click on Webcam.
And you can see that now my webcam is on.
I'm going to take some pictures of this Panda.
So I'll hold the record, and I'll get some different angles.
And then now I'll do the same for the dog.
So I'll click Hold to record, get some different angles,
and then now I can train the model.
So I'll click Train Model.
Great.
Now you can see that I can test this model to see how it does.
So now I'll give it an object that it hasn't seen before,
and it will try to figure out whether it's a panda or a dog.
Cool. And you can see that it has probabilities, but there's a higher probability that it's a panda.
Let's try this one. Here you can see it thinks it's a dog. Now I'll just try one more thing.
I guess it thinks I'm a dog.
So it's really fun, and I encourage you to try it yourself with your own objects.
So how does the machine learn?
It's using something called a model.
Let's learn more about models in the next video.