Let's say you have a mini toaster oven like this, and you want to take a piece of bread like this,
and turn it into a piece of toast like this. How would you do that? There are knobs in the toaster
oven to let you control how hot and how long to toast a piece of bread. Similarly, in machine
learning, there are these things called models that have parameters that you can adjust so that
you can get a piece of toast that looks like this and not a piece of toast that looks like this.
Let's take a closer look at machine learning models and how they learn. So what is a machine
learning model? A model is a function, meaning that it takes some input, does something to process
that input, and then produces some kind of output. And a model is a special kind of function in that
it can learn to change how it processes the input to produce the output. I'll try to describe this
model as if it's a smart mini toaster oven that can customize its temperature and timing settings
based on what kind of bread it gets as its input. So let's say you have a piece of bread that you
want to toast, and you can measure how big it is by its length and width, and also identify what
type of bread it is, for example, sourdough bread. These are inputs to the model that it will use to
help it perform its task. In machine learning vocabulary, we call these inputs features. So what
does the model use to help it perform the task? It has these things called parameters. I'm representing
these as gears that you can turn. I'll explain why in a bit. In reality, it's actually a number like
the number 0.5 or 0.75. It actually starts out randomly assigned as any number because it will
be adjusted as the model learns. Let's say, for example, one parameter is a heat parameter for
how hot to make the toaster oven. The model takes the inputs such as length, width, and type of bread,
sourdough in this case, and in combination with the heat parameter, it chooses a recommended
temperature to set the mini toaster oven based on both the features of the bread and this heat
parameter. And the model usually has many parameters. In this example, I'm just giving it two. So it also
has a time parameter. The model takes in the features of length, width, and type of bread,
and in combination with the time parameter, chooses the number of minutes to run the toaster oven. And
so the smart mini toaster oven can toast the bread based on the recommended temperature and the
number of minutes, and it outputs this piece of toast. To help the model learn, you can give it
the correct answer as feedback. So for instance, here is the ideal example of toasted bread for the
same length, width, and the type of bread, which is sourdough. In machine learning vocabulary,
the correct answer for a particular example of inputs is called a label. The model's output
and the correct answer, the label, are then fed into some kind of performance measure. So this
performance measure can output a number that quantifies how good the model's output is.
This measure of performance is then sent to what's called an optimizer. You can think of an optimizer
as a tool, in this case maybe a hand wrench, and it uses the measure of performance to then go into
the model itself and update its parameters, so that next time if the model is given the same exact
inputs, it would do better at that task in producing its output. And hopefully, even if given other
kinds of bread of different length, width, and type, the model may also learn to do better at
toasting those kinds of bread, although that's not necessarily the case. And so in order to help the
model learned to work well with lots of kinds of bread, you'd want to give it more data for it to
learn from, such as this croissant and many other kinds of bread. Something I think is helpful to
know is that AI is a collection of many categories of models that specialize in different domains or
tasks. I mention this because sometimes when we read about AI in the news, it kind of makes it
sound like AI is just one single entity that can do all sorts of things. But there are models that
have been trained specifically to take in numbers or categories such as different kinds of bread.
This is called structured data. There are also models that take in images and video. This field
of AI is called computer vision. There are models that can take in audio as inputs and produce text.
This is called automatic speech recognition and sometimes you might see this in your computer or
phone as voice dictation. There are also models that generate audio. This field of AI is called
audio generation. One common type is text-to-speech. There are models that take in and do something
useful with text and human language. This field of AI that handles human language in the form of
text as well as recognizing speech or generating speech is called natural language processing.
In the history of AI and machine learning, there are many models that researchers have designed
to work on processing text, images, audio, and numbers. There is one major category of machine
learning models, that is most likely what's used in a lot of the applications that you see today,
because it performs really well when it can learn from a lot of data. This is called a neural network.
A fundamental unit of a neural network is a neuron. A neuron contains what are called weights,
which is just another name for parameter, but the word weights is specific to neural networks. So you
can say that any model, whether it's a neural network or not, has parameters that it uses to
learn from data. And for a neural network, the parameters are called weights. You can have more
than one neuron, and combined together, they create what's called a layer. And you can have more neurons
grouped together, and they actually take the outputs of these neurons on the left as their own inputs,
so that they can produce their own outputs. These other group of neurons on the right can also be
grouped together and referred to as a layer. And a neural network can have many layers. Each layer
takes the previous layer's output as its input, and each layer sends its output to another layer
to be their input. When there are many layers in a neural network, we say that the neural network
is very deep. And another common way that people refer to neural networks is the term deep learning.
So when you hear people talk about deep learning in the news, they're really referring to machine
learning that uses these very powerful models called neural networks. So now you know how to
neural network. And if you add a blue line down here and an orange circle up here,
maybe a little red car over here, and a little birdie over here, you now also know how to draw
the Golden Gate Bridge. So there's one more thing I'd like to add. So I'd like to clarify
that models go through an explicit training phase versus an inference phase, and I'll explain what
that means. What you saw here where a model was learning, this whole picture that includes the
model, the performance measure, and the optimizer, these are all pieces that work together during
training when the model is learning from data and when you have data not just on what the inputs are
but what the correct answer should be for each given input. When models are done training,
they're ready to be used by application users like us, then you actually no longer have data
on the correct answer. You're not using the performance measure or the optimizer. So during
inference, you're giving your own input to the model, and the model is doing its best based on
what is learned during training to give you a good output to perform the desired task. But at this
point, the parameters are no longer going to be changed when you send inputs to the model. I want
to mention this because when you as a user are using some AI-enabled application, I just want to
make clear that each time you use the application, it's not automatically learning or changing its
parameters based on your inputs. Now, it is also true that companies that offer these software
applications will collect your inputs to train their model, but they usually aggregate that
information over time. They also will need to clean the data and identify the correct answers
for each input, and then they can separately train a model on that data at a later date. The main
point I want to get across is that most likely when you're using a machine learning model,
it's not going to be updating its parameters every minute or every second that you're using it.
So that was a lot of information over the past few videos, but I just want to take a step back
and describe the big picture of what you saw. AI is a field of research that enables computers to
perform tasks intelligently. Machine learning is a major subfield of AI that uses data to train
computers to perform tasks. A model is a function that performs a task by taking an input and
producing an output, and can learn from experience and data to get better at that task. If you didn't
catch everything that you saw in the past few videos, don't worry. The rest of this course is
much more focused on having you practice using AI-enabled applications and getting some conceptual
understanding of what's happening behind the scenes to do some of the pretty cool things that
you'll be able to do with AI. Coming up next, I'll give a brief study tip on looking at the big
picture, which I hope will help you give yourself more options when navigating this course. See you
in the next video.