If you have any friends who are into photography, they may love to tell you how they can use their
professional camera to blur the background in photos. If you don't have a professional camera
yourself, you can still do that with your regular phone and AI. Let's see how that works with
something called image segmentation. In most photo apps, you can create a portrait effect
by blurring the background. For example, in Google Photos, you can click on Edit and then click on
Portrait. Notice that it's blurring the image, but not the whole image, just the background behind me.
So again, here is the original image, and here is the image with the blurred background. This is
called the Bokeh effect, and people like that it helps the viewer focus their attention on the
subject of the photo. And don't worry, Bokeh effect is not an AI-related word that you need to
remember. Photographers love talking about the bokeh effect, so it's just a nice word to know
in case you're friends with a photographer. The photo app is able to identify specifically which
parts of an image represent the person in the foreground as opposed to everything else in the
background on a pixel by pixel level. And by pixel, I'm referring to all the tiny little dots that
make up a digital photograph. Here's what I mean. If you look at just a small section of the
photograph and then zoom in. Imagine if we zoomed in enough that we're actually looking at all the
pixels that make up an image. It's essentially like a spreadsheet where every cell of the spreadsheet
has a number that defines how much red, how much green, and how much blue is in that particular
pixel. And in order to generate this portrait photo effect, the software attempts to identify
for every pixel whether that pixel is part of the object in the foreground, or
or is part of the background.
So, the ability to determine which pixel represents the person and which pixel represents the
background is a computer vision task called image segmentation.
Note, I am skipping over some additional processing that goes in in order to identify the foreground
versus the background, and this is called depth perception, but it is possible to just rely on
image segmentation to create this portrait effect, so for now don't worry about remembering what
depth perception is. The output of image segmentation is actually going to be something
that looks like an image with the same height and width of the original photograph, but where each
pixel is given a value of 0 or 1. In this case, I'm representing the 1 values with the color white
and the zero values with the color black. But these can be any color for visualization purposes.
The computer itself just sees a spreadsheet-like grid of zeros and ones. So a value of one indicates
that a pixel from the original image is part of the segmented object, in this case the person.
A value of zero represents anything that was not part of the segmented object. In this case,
that's the background. This image of just zeros and ones is called a mask. You can think of it the
same way you think of a mask you wear for a costume. It outlines particular areas of the image,
just like a mask that you might wear if you're a superhero or just attending some dress-up event
outlines a certain area of your face. And this mask can then be used downstream for other steps
in the software application to process just the pixels that are the person or just the pixels that
are in the background. So here's what you can do to get the blur effect. So here's the original image,
And here is the mask. And here is where we want to store just the pixels of the person in the
foreground. For this pixel, let's say the value is 125. And in the mask, the value at that same
location is 0. So 125 times 0 is 0. And let's put a 0 here. Let's try another pixel here. Let's say
it's 150. In the mask, the value at the same location is 1. 150 times 1 is 150. So let's save
that here. And if you do that for all the pixels, you'll get an image that has the same pixels of
the subject, like this. And I'm simplifying a little bit for the sake of clarity. Normally,
for color photos, every pixel stores three values. One for how much red, how much green,
and how much blue, and that mixes together to produce the color. The next step is to go back
to the original image and blur the whole thing. Yes, the background and even the subject in the
foreground. Everything. I'll explain why in a bit. Then, take this subject that you carved out using
the segmentation mask and overlay it on top of the blurred image. And that's how you get the nice
portrait bokeh effect with a blurred background using image segmentation. Now, you may be wondering
why we take this somewhat indirect approach of getting the mask of the subject, blurring the
entire photo, and then adding the subject back on top. For instance, what if you just used the
image segmentation mask to identify all the pixels of the background behind the subject and just
directly blur those pixels? Well, let's zoom in a bit to see what might happen. The thing is,
the way the blurring effect works is kind of like dipping your finger in water and then moving it
over a watercolor painting to get the pixels to mix together.
So if you apply the blur somewhere here, that's fine.
But when you try to blur the parts of the background
that border the subject, which you don't want to be blurry,
then you'll end up blurring the pixels of the subject as well.
So if you do the recommended method that you saw earlier,
this helps you to make sure that the person in the photo
doesn't have a blurry outline around them.
Oh, and one more thing.
You can actually try out image segmentation yourself
by going to Meta AI's website.
If you start from the Meta AI chatbot site,
you can click on the left-hand menu
and then click on AI Demos.
The AI Demos page includes a section called Segment Anything.
It's currently version two
at the time that I'm filming this.
So let's click on that.
Then I'll click on the button, Try It Now.
It starts out with a default video
that's about 10 seconds long,
but I'll go here and click on the button
that says Change Video.
And there are other videos to choose from,
but I'm going to drag and drop a video of my own.
Note that for any video that you upload, it will show about the first 9 to 10 seconds of it.
So I'll go ahead and click play and take a look at the video.
Now I'm going to pause the video so that I can click on an object to segment.
And in this case, I'll click on this emoji ball in my hand.
It gives me the option to add more mouse clicks to define the object that I'm interested in.
But this looks pretty good, so I'll just go ahead and click on the button here that says track objects.
After a few seconds, it starts to play the video again.
And you can see that the emoji ball is being outlined by a blue line.
So if you click on the button that says next,
it gives you some options for things that you can do with the object that you've now segmented.
For instance, you can click on erase and then gradient.
And you can also click on pixelate.
If you click on spotlight, it looks like it's outlining the emoji ball.
If you click on burst, it looks like this.
And you can actually click on emoji.
So in this video, it's actually replacing this emoji ball with an actual emoji.
and you can cycle through a couple different emojis.
That's pretty cool.
You can also update the background,
and it would only affect the background and not the objects that are segmented.
So I'd encourage you to try it out for yourself.
Maybe you can find a fun video that you'd like to use to practice image segmentation.
Coming up next,
what if you took a picture of something that has text in it,
like an outdoor sign or a restaurant receipt,
and wanted to be able to copy that text into a text message, for instance?
Let's look at how to do that next.