Have you ever picked up a receipt or a brochure or seen a sign on the wall and found yourself
typing the text into your phone? What if instead you could take a picture of it and then let your
phone get the text from it for you? Let's take a look at optical character recognition and how it
lets you do that. Let's say you took a picture of a sign that you thought was interesting and you
want to send it to your friend, Frances Ko. Frances replies that she can't read what the
sign says and asks you to type it out. So you could try to type it out by hand, but then you remember
that you can use computer vision on your phone. So if you're using Google Photos, you can click on
the lens icon, then it looks for parts of the image that look like characters of a language,
in this case English. Then it lets you select the text that you want to further process.
So then you can click copy. Then you can go back to your message to Frances, paste in the text,
and send it. So this kind of computer vision task that looks for characters of a language
and attempts to identify and recognize those characters in order to output regular text,
this is called optical character recognition, often shortened to the acronym OCR. So what is OCR
doing? The software identifies a bounding box around each part of the image that appears to
contain a character in a language. Then, for each bounding box, it classifies that as one of those
letters. So optical character recognition is actually an application of object detection,
because it's first localizing where the text appears in an image, and then it's identifying
whether it's letter A, B, C, D, all the way to Z, as well as punctuation like commas, periods,
dollar signs, and so on. So I'd like to go back and point out one thing you might have noticed.
The text that you got from optical character recognition looked like this, and you can see here
the text doesn't seem quite understandable. First, there's this line, Leawood Walk of F,
and below that, just Holly. Let's go back to the image and take a closer look. If you zoom in,
here's part of the image that the software is having trouble with. The text is written on the
inside of a circle. Here you can see that Leawood Walk of Fame, and here is Holly. So why do you
think it output the text like this? Well, most text, like in a document or a book, is written in
straight lines. And for many languages like English, text flows from left to right, then top
to bottom. So it looks like the OCR software was detecting text from top to bottom, and it assumed
that Leawood walk of F was on one line, and the next line below that was Holly. And so one common
theme that you'll see throughout this course is that even though AI-enabled software can do pretty
cool things, you as the user and the human still play an important role in checking whether the
output makes sense, so it's still up to you to make adjustments as necessary. The other point I'd
like to make is that when something doesn't work, it might be a chance to learn. For instance,
when something like this isn't working quite right, if you can figure out why it's not working the
way you expect it to, then you might get a better understanding of how this application or this
software works and how you can use it. Another scenario where you could use optical character
recognition is when you take pictures of your receipts after you go to a restaurant or grocery
store. You can use OCR to extract the items that you purchased, as well as the prices that you paid
for them. And what if you're traveling and you took a picture of this sign at an outdoor food market?
This app has another button, Translate, and it looks like it performs OCR on parts of the image
with Chinese characters, then translate that text into English and overlays the English on top of
that. You'll learn more about machine translation later on in the rest of this course. You can also
apply these computer vision tasks that you saw in the previous couple videos on your computer inside
a web browser. If you use Google Chrome web browser, you can open up the menu on the top right and then
click on "Search with Google Lens". Select the area you want to search or extract text from and you
can copy that text. You can also translate that text and select objects and images to search as
well. Coming up next, I'll share some tips on why taking a break may help you with your studies and
your work. So please take a short break and then check out the next video to see why it's good for you.