If you want to know what kind of flower this is, one thing you can do is to take a picture of it
and then get your photo app to tell you what it is. In this case, it says it's a peony. So how does
the app do that? Let's take a look at computer vision, and in particular, object detection,
to find out more. So here's a photo that I'm viewing inside the Google Photos app. On the
bottom here, you can click on Lens, and you'll see that it creates a rectangle around an object
that it detected. And in this case, it's me. One common task in computer vision is to identify
a subsection of an image that contains an object of interest. It does this by defining a rectangle
called a bounding box that surrounds that object. And theoretically, it could also create a bounding
box around other objects of interest as well. For example, maybe over here, or maybe down here,
or maybe even back up here. This task of defining bounding boxes around objects of interest
is called object localization. Something I'd like to mention is that these bounding boxes are
usually rectangles and not other shapes like circles, triangles, or even parallelograms,
because rectangles are fairly efficient to define and work with. Another thing I'd like to note is
that object localization just identifies a region with something of interest, but doesn't yet include
the step of identifying what is within that bounding box. In other words, it tells you where
an object is within an image, but not what that object is. Here's another photograph. If I click
on lens here and then scroll down a bit, you can see that it classified this image to be either a
Maltese dog or a terrier. And by the way, his name is Tofu. This is another common task in computer
vision called image classification.
One thing to note here is that the task of classification does not include the creation
of the bounding box.
Even though in this demonstration the app has also created a bounding box around the
dog, the task of classification is just focused on identifying the name or label of an image.
The possible set of outputs of an image classifier are called classes.
Some examples of classes could be person, flower, dog, or bird, for instance.
To identify where an object is and what it is, you can combine these two tasks.
Object localization gets us these bounding boxes.
That's where these objects are located.
Then you can apply image classification on the subset of the image that's within each
bounding box.
So you get person, glasses, flower, tree, for instance.
This combination of object localization and image classification is called object detection.
Notice that for a single photograph, object detection can detect multiple objects.
There are some things worth noting when you're using an object detection app.
You may get different specificity in the class.
For instance, the class will probably be more specific than just "flower", but here you
can see that this yellow flower is identified as a dahlia.
here you can see that this class is slightly more specific. It's a Dahlia pinata. I did some
searching online and I think this yellow Dahlia is called a golden torch Dahlia. Something else
that I think is helpful to know is that the camera angle or point of view can affect the results.
For instance, this picture of this cute puppy is facing the front of his face. The image classifier
suggests that it may be a Feist, Podcake Dog, Cur, Hound, Haspen, or even a Pitbull. If I use a
picture of the same dog at a different angle, in this case this shows its body a bit more,
then the image classifier suggests that it might be a Mountain View Cur, or a Cajun Squirrel Dog,
or Black Mouth Cur. And by the way, this puppy's name is Neo. You may also see different or better
results if you adjust the bounding box manually. For instance, here, given the default bounding box,
you don't see any text that suggests what type of bird it is, you just see some similar looking
images, and you'll learn more about these search results in the next video. But if you manually
adjust the bounding box, usually making it fit more closely around the object, then you might
get better results. So now, the image classifier gives some suggested classes: Humboldt Penguin,
African penguin, and penguin. So you've probably noticed that below the image classifier results,
you can see similar images. The photo app is performing another type of task
called similarity search. Let's take a look at similarity search in the next video.