When you're using an object detection service such as Google Lens, you'll notice that below
the suggested classes of the image classifier, you'll see search results for similar images.
So, these white fluffy dogs look similar to the original white fluffy dog. Similarly,
after the suggested classes for this cute brown dog, you can see similar images of other cute
brown dogs. This is called similarity search, and you can apply this to finding similar images and
also to finding similar audio or similar text. Let's get a brief conceptual overview of how
similarity search works. What if you tried to use a single number to represent any image in order to
help you compare and contrast any two images? Let's just pick a feature and draw a number line. For
So for this dog, you might assign it a number 1, whereas for this dog, you might assign it a number 6.
So you give this dog a higher number because in the image, it appears to have more brown fur compared to the other dog.
Now what if you can represent the image with not one, but two numbers?
So in addition to the amount of brown fur, you could draw another number line to represent the amount of white fur.
So this image of the first dog here might have a number 7 assigned to that image, and this
dog here might have a number 2 assigned to the image.
You may have heard the saying "birds of a feather flock together" but have you also
heard the saying "dogs of the same fur frolic together"?
Probably not, because I just made that up.
But I hope this helps you remember that if you take more images of dogs and try to place
them in the space defined by these two number lines, then you might have a dog here on the bottom left,
maybe this dog will be placed here on the right, and this dog here might appear somewhere on the
bottom left, and this dog might appear over here on the bottom right. Notice that dogs with a similar
amount of brown fur appear closer to each other, and dogs with white fur also appear closer to each
other in this space. Now in practice, we don't as humans choose these specific features for these
number lines. Instead, we have machine learning models do that for us, because then we get better
results. Whenever you train a machine learning model to perform a task on an image, you get a
fairly useful byproduct from this. For example, if you have an image classification model, you can
give it an input like this, and it outputs a class such as the text "cute dog". In order for the model
to perform this image classification task, it creates a representation of the important features
that help it to decide that this is a cute dog. This representation is actually a list of numbers,
maybe a few hundred to a few thousand numbers. And this is still pretty small if you consider that a
photograph may contain 9 million pixels, which are 9 million numbers times 3 because there's red,
green, and blue for every pixel. This list of numbers that a model creates in order to represent
the image in a compact way is called an embedding. So if you use those embeddings and treat them like
coordinates in space, you can place each image somewhere in that space. Here, I'm just showing
a two-dimensional space so that we can see it on a two-dimensional slide. So it would just be two
numbers representing an image. But with embeddings of 200 to 300 numbers, the math is similar.
If you draw a line from the location of this image to the location of this other image,
this line shows how far apart those two images are. If you draw a line between these two images,
that line also shows how far apart they are. And in this case, they're further apart compared to
the first line. You can measure the distance between any two images as the distance between
their two embeddings. And this class is more focused on getting a conceptual understanding
as well as practical use of AI. So I'm not getting into the math here, but it's probably math that
you've seen at some point in school. And since you may or may not want to relive your memories of
math class, I won't get into it here. So let's just clarify the difference between image classification
and similarity search with images. With image classification, if you give it the image of a dog,
it will output some class, such as the text cute dog. In contrast, if you give an image to a
similarity search database, then it will first create an embedding that represents that image
with a small list of numbers. And then it can search through a database of other dogs, where
each dog in the database has an embedding generated to represent it. Based on the distance
between the embedding of the input dog and the embedding of each dog in the database,
the similarity search database can retrieve a list of dogs that have the shortest distance
between them and the dog being searched. So here's a quick quiz. Who gave the dog a name?
the image classifier, and who let the dogs out, the similarity search database.
Next, what if you want to go beyond a bounding box and identify every single pixel that belongs
to this dog, or every pixel that belongs to this dog?
To learn more about how, let's take a look at image segmentation in the next video.