Oh, hello there. I was just enhancing my productivity. Really? Wait, wait, wait, hold on.
Let me explain something called incubation theory. What if you're working on a problem or a task,
and it's really hard, and you're spending a lot of time on it? One thing you could do
is to just keep trying to figure out the answer. Don't take breaks, don't sleep, don't eat,
and just keep working at it until you get the solution. Another approach is to take a break,
relax, do something else, take a nap, get some food, maybe give yourself a day to sleep on it,
then come back to the problem. What you might find when you try this out is that taking that break
actually helps you get the insight or new perspective to help you with that task. So why
is that psychologists have looked into why this happens, and here are what their studies suggest.
One idea is called unconscious thought. Even when you're not actively thinking about solving a
particular task, your mind is still processing that information. Occasionally, your mind will
jump back in and maybe daydream about that topic or task. This time spent daydreaming helps you
think differently to help you with your task. Another concept is called remote association.
For example, let's say you're very familiar with ice cream and you're also very familiar with cakes.
One day, you realize that you can combine ice cream and cake to create ice cream cake.
So when you give yourself that time to step away from a task or problem, it allows your brain to make connections between things that may help you.
Another idea is rest and recovery.
When you give yourself a break, this allows your brain to recover so that it can perform better when you go back to the task.
And there's also something called selective forgetting.
Sometimes, when you're trying to solve a problem, you may take a path that leads to a dead end.
Selective forgetting, the way a goldfish is able to forget, may free up your brain to choose a different path to perform the task.
So all of these ideas are collectively part of something psychologists call incubation theory.
Incubation theory suggests that you step away from your task, let it sit or incubate, and
then when you come back, it will hatch into a baby chick.
Or you'll find more and possibly better ways to perform a task.
So the steps you might take are the following.
First, try to solve the problem.
This helps you better understand the problem and possible solutions.
That's called preparation.
Then take a break.
That's called incubation.
Taking a break could be switching to a different task.
Preferably something that allows you to free up your mind enough to daydream and occasionally
still think about the task you're trying to solve.
It could also include exercise, which also helps your brain's performance in general.
It could be sleeping, such as taking short naps.
You might find that you get some ideas in your dreams or as you're waking up from a
dream.
After you give your brain some time to incubate, then you reach the idea that's called illumination.
Then you can check if your solution, your new idea, is correct and if it works.
That's called the verification step.
So next time you're feeling stuck, maybe take a short break.
And you may find that's exactly what you needed.
Coming up next, you'll learn about machine translation.