It's a piece of cake.
I'm on the same page. I spilled the beans. I think I bit off more than I can chew.
I let the cat out of the bag.
I'm still on the same page.
Some phrases have a direct word-for-word literal meaning, but they also have an alternative
implied or figurative meaning as well.
These are called idioms.
Let's take a look at how machine translation handles idioms.
If you go to Google Translate and translate from English "a piece of cake" to Italian,
you'll get "un pezzo di torta" which is a slice of cake.
If you add this in front to make it "it was a piece of cake" the Italian translation
becomes "un gioco da ragazzi" a game for children.
And if you add a sentence in front of that "she asked me if I could eat the grapefruit"
then "piece of cake" gets translated back into "a slice of cake" and I'm going to hide
save it for the end of the lecture, but if I make one tiny change, then it goes back again to
a game for children. So what's going on here? The phrase "a piece of cake" is an idiom which has
cultural meaning beyond the word-for-word literal meaning that it's a slice of sweet baked dessert.
Let's take a closer look at idioms and how translation models handle them. So here's a
piece of cake. In Italian, we say "un pezzo di torta". In French, this is "un par du gâteau".
In Arabic, this is "kutatun minal kake". In Chinese, this is "i kuei tangao". In Japanese, this is "keeki hito kire".
In Spanish, this is "un pedazo de pastel". This is the literal translation of the phrase "piece of cake"
in that it's not assuming any cultural meaning associated with it. Now let's see some alternative
translations for piece of cake in these same languages.
In Italian, as you saw earlier, it's "un gioco da ragazzi" which literally means "a
game for children" or "child's play".
In French, it's "se du gâteau" which means "it's some cake".
It's almost the same as the literal translation that you saw earlier.
And there are other idioms with a similar meaning which you'll learn about when you
get to the lessons about chatbots.
In Arabic, this is "sehlel mithl shorbatin ma'an" and that means "easy as drinking water".
In Chinese, it's "siao cai i dia" which literally means "a side dish".
In Japanese, it's "asamishimae" which means "before breakfast" as in "so easy, you can
do it before breakfast".
In Spanish, it's "pan komedo" which literally means "eaten bread".
These are idioms in their respective languages.
And these particular idioms are used to describe something that's easy to do.
For example, I took this intro course about modern AI, and it was a piece of cake.
So let's take another look at these translations in action and try to think about how these
phrases can be interpreted, whether they're idiomatic or literal.
If it's just the phrase "it's a piece of cake", there isn't enough context to know
whether it's being used as an idiom or if it's a literal meaning.
In this case, the model decides that you might mean this literally.
Now when you add "it was" to the front, the model seems to decide that in this case,
it might be interpreted as the expression, the idiom.
So it finds the equivalent idiom in Italian: "a game for children" or "child's play".
If you add this sentence in front: "She asked me if I could eat the grapefruit, since what
follows is: it was a piece of cake."
The previous sentence provides context that perhaps what she said was a grapefruit is
in fact not a grapefruit but a slice of cake.
And now, to change it back to the idiomatic expression again, I actually just added a
period.
As you saw in the earlier lesson about context, you can see now that machine learning models
are not following strict rules but are trying to produce sensible output based on what they've
learned from looking at previous examples.
So it's not as if adding a period to the end of an idiom will always signal to the
model that it should use the idiomatic translation. In fact, it might be fun for you to try an idiom
of your choice and add context around it to try to change it back and forth between the idiomatic
and literal translation. Next, let's take a look at the distance between two words and how that
affects the translation.