Do you speak English?
Wouldn't it be nice if you had a translator when you needed one?
Well, thankfully, if you have a phone or computer, you actually do.
Where is the bathroom?
O se trouven les toilettes?
Let's take a closer look at machine translation.
If you send a Spanish word, llamas, to a translation service, like Google Translate, you might get this:
this. "Lamas" in Spanish means "flames" in English. And if you add this, "Lamas adorables"
is translated to "Adorable llamas" in English. The flames have been replaced with "lamas".
And if you remove this and add this, you get "como te llamas" in Spanish, which means "What
is your name" in English. So, no llamas and no flames either. So what's going on here?
Let's take a closer look at how machine translation interprets individual words.
For many words, you wouldn't really need machine translation.
You could just look it up in a bilingual dictionary.
"Salad" in English is "ensalada" in Spanish.
"Eat" in English is "comer" in Spanish.
And "fresh" in English is "fresco" or "fresca".
But let's look at this word, "light".
You could translate it to "la luz" as in "light from sunlight" or "light from a light bulb".
And you could also translate this to "ligera" as in "light as a feather".
And as you saw earlier, "llamas" can be translated to "flames" as in "flames at a campfire".
Or it could also be translated to "llamas" the cute animals with long necks.
Or "llamas" can be part of this phrase "como te llamas" where "llamas" means "to call oneself".
So "como te llamas" is Spanish for "what is your name?"
So there are some words that look the same and sound the same.
Here's one more example.
The word "bank" in English could be translated to "banco" as in a financial institution
where you can deposit your money.
It could also be translated to "orilla" which is the land next to a river.
And to make things even more fun, the Spanish word for "banco" can be a bank where you
deposit your money, but can also be a bench that you sit on at a park.
These words, light, llamas, bank, banco, are examples of two or more distinct words with
their own distinct meanings that happen to look the same and also sound the same.
If two distinct words have the same spelling and pronunciation, they're called homonyms.
There are also words that look the same but don't necessarily sound the same.
Here's an example: This word could be pronounced "tear" as in "It's tearing up my heart when
I'm with you. And that could be translated to "se me parte", although apparently there are many
words that you can use to describe a broken heart. This word could also be pronounced "tear" as in
"save your tears for another day". And the Spanish for that is "lágrima". In this case, there are two
distinct words "tear" and "tear" with different meanings and they look the same but in this case
don't sound the same. When two distinct words have the same spelling and "may" or "may not" have the
pronunciation, these are called homographs. So homonyms are a special case of homographs that
not only look the same but sound the same. You don't need to remember these specific terms when
you're learning about AI, but it helps to remember that when two distinct words at least look the
same, then this can be a challenging task for a machine translation service. Now let's go beyond
single words and look at a sentence. In English, I ate the salad when translated to Hindi is this:
If we don't know anything about Hindi, then we might guess that each of these three words are
I ate the salad. But let's play the audio.
It actually sounds like the middle word is "salad" instead of "ate".
So "I ate the salad" is translated to "many salad kaya".
If you match up the words, "I" is "many the salad" "salad ate" "kaya".
So it's literally "I ate."
In English, sentences follow the pattern "subject", "verb", then the object that the verb is acting on.
"I ate the salad."
In Hindi, the pattern is "subject object verb" as in "I ate."
Japanese is also similar in that the verb comes after the object.
So, word order varies depending on which language you're translating from and to.
Let's look at something called dropped pronouns.
I ate, in English, is yo comi in Spanish.
I ate the salad is comi la ensalada.
Notice that the word yo just disappeared.
Yo, what's up with that?
I ate the fresh salad is comi la ensalada fresca.
Let's take a closer look at this.
The English, I ate the fresh salad, translates in Spanish to yo comi la ensalada fresca.
So this is I ate the salad fresh.
So this is another example of word order differences.
In English, the adjective goes first, followed by the noun.
This is the same for other languages like Chinese, Japanese, and Korean.
In Spanish, the noun comes first, followed by the adjective salad fresh.
This is the same for other languages like French, Arabic, and Hindi.
So again, the word order depends on the language that you're translating from or translating to.
And you may have noticed that the word yo disappeared earlier.
In Spanish, you can drop the pronoun yo and it would read just fine as
Comí la ensalada fresca.
Languages like Spanish, Chinese, and Japanese that let you drop the pronoun in sentences
are called pro-drop languages.
Now, you don't need to remember the term pro-drop,
But the point of these examples is to show you how word order, and even whether a word
needs to appear or not, makes the task of translating both interesting and complicated.
And so these are things to look out for whenever you use a translation service.
Coming up next, the context surrounding a word can affect how it's translated.
To get more context on what I'm talking about, please go on to the next video.