What do you think this is?
What if you interact with it and play around with it?
Now what do you think this is?
Just as interacting with an object will help you better learn what it is and how it works,
interacting with AI will also help you better learn about it too.
When you're learning about AI, or anything really,
I recommend thinking like a detective and checking if the app or model is doing what you think it is.
For example, would you accept this translation as it's given, or do you want to explore this a bit more?
First, you can take a closer look.
Let's look at each of these sentences one by one.
Some of these phrases appear to be idioms, or expressions with cultural meaning beyond their literal word-for-word meaning.
Let's make this easier to inspect by breaking this up into smaller pieces.
So let's remove the first and last sentence and keep the middle one.
And try to change the input, whatever options you can change, one at a time.
For example, I'll change this from
And look, the translation changed from
If you've taken the earlier lessons, you may recall that
Jogo da ragazzi is a child's game or child's play, and un pezzo di torta means a slice of cake.
So make changes one at a time, and maybe you can look for patterns. For example, if you change it to
I realized it was a piece of cake, the translation model assumes the idiomatic meaning of this phrase.
If you change it to I saw that it was a piece of cake, it interprets this as the literal translation.
If you change it to, I recognized that it was a piece of cake, the model goes back to the idiomatic translation.
So you can now see that when the sentence is about what I realize or recognize, something describing what's in my mind, the translation model uses the idiomatic equivalent.
When the word choice sounds more like it's what I see in front of me with my eyes, it uses the literal translation.
And it's still helpful, maybe even more helpful, to notice when the model doesn't work or doesn't fit a pattern.
For instance, if you change it to, I could see that it was a piece of cake, even though
it's technically another version of I saw with my eyes, this gets interpreted as the
idiom, a piece of cake.
I recommend one way to test out an app or task is to give inputs where you know what
the desired result would be.
Then you'll have a way to check whether it's working as expected or doing something unexpected.
Coming up next, you'll learn about chatbots, how they behave, and how you can make the
of using them. This practice of thinking like a detective will help you when you learn about
and interact with chatbots. See you soon!