Dear esteemed president of the Furry Friends Forever Cat Cafe.
Ooh, hey you! Who's a good boy? You're a good boy!
Have you ever noticed how you choose different words depending on who you're talking to?
Let's take a look at how the context affects how a word is translated.
In some languages, like French, there is a formal way to address someone and an informal way as well.
For example, let's say I'm interested in addressing a friend and I told my friend,
Since you like eating salads, I will give you an apple for your birthday.
In French, the informal way to say you is to.
This T' here is short for te, which is the version of you that is receiving the action of the verb to offer.
And this ton here means your.
When you're addressing someone in a special position,
such as a teacher, manager, or public figure,
you might use the formal way to address them.
For example,
I told my queen, since you like eating salads,
I will give you an apple for your birthday.
The formal word for you is vous,
and the formal word for your is votre.
But if you look over here,
it appears that the translation is still using the informal word for you.
So I'm going to hide what I'm changing for now because it will make more sense at the end of this video.
But you can see on the right that now it's addressing the queen with the formal words vous and votre.
In real life, whether you're addressing your friend or addressing a queen,
this context affects which words you use.
And machine translation models also use context to decide which word to use.
Let's take a closer look at context in the context of machine translation.
Here's that sentence addressing your friend in English.
And here is its translation in French.
So the word for you is tu, the other you is t' and your is ton.
These are the informal versions of the French word for you.
Here's that same sentence but now addressing my queen.
The French translation is this.
The word for you is vous and the word for your is votre.
This is the formal version of you.
If you're a French speaker, you would pick up on the word queen to recognize that the word for you should be the formal version.
For the machine translation model, the word queen is relevant context for the words you and your.
The words surrounding any given word are called the context.
You may have heard the word context before.
For example, let's say a professional singer says,
For lunch, I ate a kid's meal.
And then a gossip magazine publishes an article titled,
famous pop star heard saying, for lunch, I ate a kid. This is an example of the celebrity's
statement being taken out of context, because kid's meal is an important part of the context
of what that person was actually saying. But you may recall that the translation model did not pick
up on the fact that the queen might need to be addressed formally. So it's still using the
informal word to for you. So let's try to give the translation model more context. So again,
it's starting out with the informal words for you. Let's try to add the word formal in square
brackets after the first u. That doesn't work. Let me undo that so I can test out one change at a
time. Now I'll try to replace u with the formal French word vous. That also doesn't change the
translation. So I'll again undo this change so that I can test each change one at a time. Now
I'll change the lowercase q in queen to an uppercase q. It's still not enough context. Let's undo
everything for now. There's a saying I heard recently, which is everything, everywhere,
all at once. So let's try to use all three changes to give the translation model more context.
So let's change you to vous, add formal in square brackets, and capitalize the q in queen.
Et voilà! Finally, with all these hints, the translation app has now figured out that you're
asking it to use the formal words for you and your in French. And by the way, if you don't know what
"voilà" means there might be an app that can help you. The main point I hope you take from this
is to experiment with these models in order to better understand how they behave and also how
they sometimes don't behave. You'll start to notice how the apps that rely on machine learning models
are not always following explicit rules, so the changes I made here to get the effects that you
saw here may not be the only way to do it and also may not work in all situations. Next, you'll look
Look at the difference between translating a phrase word for word as opposed to translating
the meaning behind that phrase.
This will be fun.
I promise it will be a slice of sweet baked dessert.