Can you see the facial expression on this emoji ball?
How about this emoji ball?
And how about this emoji ball?
Just as the distance between you and another object can affect how well you can see it,
the distance between two words in a piece of text can affect how well a machine translation can figure out the relationship between those two.
Let's see an example of that.
You've seen how the context of other words around any given word has an influence on how that word is translated.
Something helpful to keep in mind is that the distance between these two words can affect how much influence one word has on the other.
Here's a small piece of text.
She asked,
Who ate the salad?
I replied,
It looked delicious, so I ate it.
In Spanish, the word for salad is la ensalada, and the word it refers to a salad.
In Spanish, it is translated to the word la.
I'm going to add some text, which I'm hiding for now,
but if you increase the distance between the word for salad and the word for it,
notice at the bottom, the word for it went from la to lo.
This is an interesting aspect of language and language translation
that will be helpful for you to know as you verify the results that you get
from a machine translation model.
So let's take a closer look.
In Spanish, the word for it is either lo when it's referring to a word that has a masculine gender,
or it's la when it refers to a noun that has a feminine gender.
When the pronoun for it matches the gender of the noun that it's referring to, this is called gender agreement.
And something interesting happens when the pronoun and the noun that it's referring to are too far apart.
The translation model may no longer be able to recognize the connection between those two words anymore.
So here you see I've added a bunch of text in the middle.
The result is it now says lo, the masculine version for it, when it should say la, the feminine pronoun for it.
The adjective delicious is now delicioso when it should be the feminine gendered deliciosa.
And it seems to default to the masculine gender when it's not sure.
So this is just something important to keep in mind when you're reviewing the translations that you get from a machine learning model.
And just if you're curious, in natural language processing, this task of making sure that pronouns and adjectives are aligned,
or generally to determine when two pieces of text are referring to the same thing, such as a salad,
this task is called co-reference resolution.
And you see here that co-reference resolution can become more challenging when the two pieces of text are much further apart from each other.
Something fun for you to try is to see what other ways of inserting text between the noun and its
pronoun can make it more challenging for the translation model to maintain that connection
between the two. Here is just a demonstration of what I was doing in order to see if I could break
the connection between the word for salad and the word for it. Next up is a short study tip,
think like a detective. I've spent the past few years coaching engineers to be good teachers,
and I've often asked them to think like a detective,
so I'd like to share the same advice with you as well.