Say you have a logic problem that you want the chatbot to solve, and you can choose two
slightly different ways to write the last sentence of your prompt. Give your answer,
then give your reasoning. Alternatively, give your reasoning, then give your answer. Here is the logic
problem, and don't worry, I'll talk to the details a bit later, so for now, all you need to know is
is that the correct answer is no.
Now let's see how a chatbot responds when I give it this logic problem
where the last sentence is written in one of these two ways.
So I'll show this text more clearly in a bit,
but on the left, it answers yes, which is incorrect.
On the right, it answers no, which is correct.
Why is that?
The way chatbots produce their output is by predicting the next word,
one at a time.
Let's look at that in more detail and see how you can tailor your prompts to make the
most of this behavior.
Let's see what it means for a chatbot to predict the next word.
Here I'm using hugging chat to use a model from Mistral AI.
My input prompt will be "twinkle twinkle little" and the completion is * how I wonder
what you are and so on.
This is why the output is called a completion because the early versions of chatbots learned
to take an incomplete start of a sentence and to predict the next words that would complete the
rest of that sentence. So a chatbot takes your input, the prompt, and it doesn't output its entire
completion all at once. It actually outputs a word or part of a word at a time. So given the input
twinkle twinkle little, it outputs star, then it appends its own output to the initial prompt. So
it outputs another word or part of a word, in this case, the word how.
And it repeats this process, appending its own output to the accumulated text,
which is now twinkle twinkle little star how.
And it uses that entire input to help it predict the next word, which is I, and so on and so on.
So you might notice that you're probably not used to writing prompts this way,
because you're used to already writing them as instructions, as in,
please give me information or summarize this piece of text.
But before chatbots were explicitly trained to follow human-like instructions,
like perform this task,
the way they would normally work is they would just try to complete a piece of text.
For example, given twinkle twinkle little,
it tries to figure out that the next word is probably star,
and then the other words following will be how I wonder what you are.
This has implications for how a chatbot performs a task.
Let's revisit that logic problem in more detail.
Here's the logic problem.
My friend and I have eight additional friends who wish to go to a restaurant.
My car fits four people.
My friend's car fits five people.
No one else has cars.
It takes 20 minutes to drive to the restaurant.
Can we all get to the restaurant with our cars in 20 minutes?
So the number of people to transport is me plus my friend plus eight more or 10 people.
The number of seats in the cars is 4 plus 5 or 9.
The correct answer should be no.
Now let's look at the two outputs of the same model when given the same logic problem,
but with the last instruction worded differently.
On the left, where it was prompted with give your answer, then give your reasoning, it says
yes, we can all get to the restaurant within 20 minutes.
It goes through some reasoning that so far appears to be correct.
Then it says this.
This leaves one person remaining who can accompany either you or your friend in their respective cars.
So here is where the reasoning is going wrong in order to justify its answer of yes.
Now let's look at the response on the right side, where the chatbot was prompted with
give your reasoning, then give your answer.
It starts by calculating that there are a total of 10 people,
and also continues with leaving one person without a ride.
It also correctly states that it is not possible to transport all 10 people to the restaurant
in 20 minutes.
Then it gives the answer no.
Now that you know that the chatbot predicts one word at a time, and it can look back at
all of its previously predicted words to predict the next one, you might be able to see what's
going on.
If it gives the answer first, then thinks through the logic problem, it won't be able to use
all of its reasoning to help it give that answer, because it already gave the answer. In fact, in this
case, it's now just trying to justify its original answer, even if the reasoning is wrong. On the
other hand, if you ask it to go through its reasoning first, it can use all of its reasoning
as additional information in order for it to better answer the question. So how can you make
use of this behavior when prompting a chatbot? Well, if some tasks that you can ask a chatbot to do
can help it perform another task, then ask it to perform those helpful tasks first. For example,
you can prompt, give your reasoning first, then give your answer. Another example is, review what
you know about this topic, write an outline, then write an article. Can you think of other examples?
And one more thing. In the field of natural language processing, the task of predicting the
next word is called language modeling. What does it mean to model a language? If you can iteratively
predict the next word in a piece of text and make it sound like human-produced text, then you're
modeling that language. And if you get a model to learn how to predict the next word, then it's a
language model. Very recently, AI researchers found that if they used really large models with a lot
of text data and get them to learn about language by predicting the next word, then these models
could learn to not just predict the next word, but also do many other tasks, from translating to other
languages to summarizing text and more. So that's why these things are called large language models
or LLMs for short. And you can give the large language model a hint about what tasks you wanted
to do within the input itself. If you recall when you used a machine translation tool, you would
just give it a piece of text and it would translate it to another language based on the language you
chose from a drop down menu. With a language model within the text itself, you can give it an
instruction like translate to French followed by a piece of text and the
model will then figure out that you want it to perform a translation task and if
you wanted to do another task like summarize a long movie script you can
include the instruction summarize this movie script as part of your input this
is directing or prompting the model to perform a certain task and that's why
the inputs to large language models are called prompts.
Next up, let's look at what happens when large language models make stuff up that isn't true.
You'll learn about hallucinations next.