If you are asked a question that you don't quite know the answer to,
what would you say if you have to give an answer?
For example, on which side did you see the purple emoji ball?
Was it on your left side or on the right side?
Now you may not have enough information to answer this question,
but you may try to give a reasonable answer.
Similarly, machine learning models and chatbots as well try their best to perform a task,
sometimes they get it wrong. When a chatbot makes up something that isn't quite right,
it's called a hallucination. Let's see more examples of hallucinations. Oh, and by the way,
there was no purple emoji ball. In August 2024, the Olympic Games were held in Paris.
At the time of filming this course, I'm using models that were trained on information that
had a cutoff point before the Olympic Games happened, which means that these models were
not trained on any information that happened during these Olympic events. Here I'm going to
use Meta AI. I'll ask some questions about the Olympic Games. Who won medals at the Paris Olympics?
Who are some of the people who won medals at the Paris Olympics? I'm noticing here that it says
for the silver medal winners, it mentions Noah Lyles in the men's 200 meters. I'll ask another
question who won medals in the men's 200 meters it says that arian knight and won gold noah lyle's
won silver and let's seal tabogo won bronze in the men's 200 meter events at the paris olympics
let's watch a replay of that race i'm watching a youtube video provided by nbc sports
final demands 200 is away benard responded very well to the gun he's gotten out well
But now here comes Noah Lyles.
Lyles in the middle of the track.
Tobongo is going with Benarek.
Noah Lyles said this is where he gets to show his speed.
His coming speed.
There's Eriksen.
Tobongo.
So it actually looks like Letil Tobongo won the gold, not bronze.
Kenneth Bednarek won silver.
And Noah Lyles won bronze, not silver.
Arian Knighton placed fourth and not first.
So why did this happen?
Large language models have some randomness built in, so for the same input prompt, the output
completion is a bit different every time. Let's take a look at an example of this in OpenAI's
Playground. I'll enter the prompt here, which is, a city I want to visit is. Then the model will
continue outputting the completion right after the prompt. First, it says San Diego, and if I click on
San Diego, it has a drop-down menu which shows other possible words the model was considering
using, including all these other cities, as well as a percentage, which indicates how likely it
thinks each word is likely to be the next word to come next. If I do this again, it says Tokyo,
then it says Rome, then Seattle, then Amsterdam, and then Paris. Notice that there's no way for
the model to read my mind and know what city I want to visit, and so it's making an educated guess
based on other texts that it's learned from that these cities that it's proposing are places that
many people have said they want to visit. This OpenAI Playground also shows the percent probability
assigned to each word, which is the model's estimate of how likely that word should appear
next. But it doesn't always just pick the word that has the highest probability. Let's take a
closer look. The input is, a city I want to visit is. The model gathers a list of possible options
for the next word, and then it randomly samples from that list, giving some weight or consideration
to the probability assigned to each word or part of a word. For TOK, it likely is the beginning of
the word for Tokyo. BAR is likely the beginning of the word for Barcelona. From what you saw a moment
ago, the model randomly sampled the word Paris and then appended that at the end of the initial
prompt, and this allows it to move on to randomly sampling the next word after that. So you can see
that the chatbot is just doing its best to try and look at what text it was given and then try
to predict the next word that has some reasonable likelihood of making sense. This is fine when
you're not expecting it to make some factually correct claim. For instance, any of these cities
that it mentions sound like cities that I would like to visit. But when the model is making a
statement that is a factual claim, and when what it says is not factually correct, then this is
called a hallucination. It's easier to notice when a chatbot is saying something incorrect when you
ask it about a topic that you know well, and when it's also a topic that the chatbot may not have
about. So in this case, I'll ask it about myself. Who is Eddie Xu? So it says that I am a YouTuber
who talks about smartphones and laptops and other tech gadgets, and it also says that I'm very
popular. Oh, and by the way, I'm very flattered, but none of those things are true. Now, it's
easier for me to fact check this because I've done web searches of my name and of the people who have
my name, including myself, and nobody fits this very flattering description, although maybe it's
something to aspire to someday. If you want, you can try to ask a chatbot to describe who you are
and see what it says. There's one more thing I'd like to note, which is that if a chatbot says
something that's off topic and not answering your question, then even if it's factually correct,
this completion is also considered a kind of hallucination. One way to think about this is
that a chatbot might be hallucinating a question that you didn't even ask, and so it's answering
that question instead of answering your question. Here's an example of this. I'm using the downloadable
app LM Studio and using it to download a compressed version of the Nemo Mistral model. And don't worry,
you'll learn soon about how you can download models onto your own computer, as well as what
a compressed model is. So I'll ask it, what are some highlights of the Paris Olympics? It first
mentions the 2024 Olympics, but then the rest of the completion is about the 1900 and 1924 Olympics,
which also occurred in Paris. So it can be a bit debatable whether this is considered an
off-topic response because I didn't specify the 2024 Olympics in the prompt. But if you use a
chatbot often enough, you may notice that it sometimes appears to be answering a different
question and not the one you were asking. So I encourage you to try testing out prompts that you
think may lead a chatbot to hallucinate and then practice fact-checking its response as it will
help you to develop a good habit of anticipating and identifying when the chatbot's output isn't
quite right. Next, let's look at how memory affects the chatbot's most recent responses.
I'll see you in the next video.