If you learn how to write a love letter to your significant other really well, this will make life really great.
If you learn how to write a prompt to a chatbot really well, then life will be pretty nice too.
Let's take a look at some tips on how to write your prompts.
The first thing you might find helpful is that you can prompt in the language of your choice.
It doesn't have to be in English.
For example, you can ask in Chinese, what's the difference between a Shih Tzu and a Havanese dog?
四肢圈和 Havanachuan有什么区别?
You can ask in French, what's the difference between a Shih Tzu and a Havanese dog?
quelle est la différence entre un Shih Tzu et un Sean Havanais?
Certain models have more training emphasis on certain languages.
Mistral AI, for instance, is based in France,
and they focus their model training to make it perform well in several European languages,
including French, German, Italian, and Spanish.
Another general tip I would recommend is to write more text than you normally would
compared to when you're doing a web search.
A lot of us have been transitioning from doing web searches
to doing searches and requesting information from chatbots.
So for instance, you might initially have a prompt like this.
What is the difference between a Shih Tzu and a Havanese dog?
Let's see what you get from this prompt.
So it answers the question and is fairly concise.
But you can think about what you're looking for in the answer.
Maybe ask it some intermediate steps that might help it to give a more complete answer,
such as list out similarities and differences.
And perhaps you can share what you plan to do with the information you get.
For example, ask it for advice on how to distinguish one thing from another.
Let's see what you might get with a more detailed prompt.
So you can see that it follows the guidance of the more detailed prompt
and lists similarities and differences,
then explains how to tell them apart.
So if you can be more detailed in what you're asking for,
then the chatbot will better understand what you're looking for and try to respond accordingly.
Another general suggestion is to break down your task into a sequence of subtasks.
For instance, you can ask what's the difference between these two types of dogs
and give it a list of steps that you might have taken to answer this question yourself.
First, review reference material, then list out similarities and differences,
And finally, suggest how to tell them apart.
And let's see what you might get.
And you can see at the top, it says, searched two sites,
meaning that it took those two web links that were provided
and looked through those in order for it to answer the question.
And notice that there is a logical sequence to the subtasks.
The earlier tasks involve research and gathering information.
Those come before the later tasks that involve using that information to draw conclusions.
And you can also describe how you want the output to be organized or formatted,
whether it's a table or bullet points or numbered list.
For example, you can ask, format your response in a table with these rows and these columns,
and answer this part of the question with a list of bullet points.
So this is quite helpful because by default, you'll most likely get either paragraphs
or sometimes bullet points, but if you want something different, then you can just ask for
that. Let's see what you might get with a prompt like this. So Gemini produces a nice looking table,
and on top of that, you may notice that it gives you an option to export into Google Sheets. Then
it provides a list of bullet points as requested. In addition to the format of the output, you can
also set expectations for what you consider to be a good response or good outcome. Most chatbots,
default tend to reply in a somewhat confident tone and will try their best to give some answer,
but you can set expectations that you would rather it admit when it's not sure or does not have enough
information. In other words, what you consider to be a good answer is sometimes to say "I don't know."
Let's first see what happens when you don't set the expectation and see how it differs when you do
set the expectation. So I'll just give it that top half of the prompt and not the bottom half.
Here's what you might get if you ask it to describe similarities and differences for the following categories.
You might be thinking that the question about smell and taste is not as common as the category about appearance,
and that there's probably less information about how dogs smell or what kind of food they prefer over others.
But a chatbot may still try its best to give a reasonable answer.
Now let's see how the same chatbot will respond if you do include your expectation that when it's not sure, it should say so.
So you can see that in the case of taste, it does admit that it's not 100% sure about
specific differences.
Another recommendation is to add structure to your prompts.
For instance, you can add subheaders to your prompts such as references and steps.
You can include numbering and bullet points as well.
You can also use special characters around text that you think should be treated differently
than its surrounding text.
For example, you may want to make it clear when a web link starts and ends, and so you
can put angle brackets around them.
And you can choose any special characters to do this.
A common recommendation is to use three double quotes at the start and end, or use three
hashtags at the start and the end.
These special characters that define the start and end of some specific piece of text are
called delimiters.
Let's try out this prompt.
And here, for instance, Cohere's chatbot interface lets you choose tools like Web Scraper, which
allows the chatbot to look up web pages that you give it links to.
Don't worry about the other tools right now, you'll learn more about tools later in the
So I'll go ahead and put in the prompt.
Notice how it indicates that it's using the URL scraper twice, one for each web link that's
given in the prompt.
One nice feature in Cohere's web interface is that you can highlight different parts
of its output, and it can give you the reference to the article where it got the information.
and it can help you verify that the output is grounded in the references that you asked it to
read. Another interesting feature of chatbots is that you can give them a temporary role or persona
that affects how they perform the task. You can say, you are a veterinarian, and then ask this
question. Or you can say, you are a comedian, and ask the same question. Let's go ahead and use a
model called Nemo by the company NVIDIA. So let's see if we can find Nemo. So here's Mistral AI's
website. Mistral AI actually teamed up with NVIDIA to train a model called Mistral Nemo, which is
based on NVIDIA's large language model Nemo. If I click on the current model, which is called
Mistral Large 2, it shows the models available. And look, I found Mistral Nemo here. So I'll first
give it a persona of a veterinarian, and let's see what it says. It gives a fairly structured answer
with different subheaders that includes its health and lifespan. Now let's try again by giving it the
persona of a comedian who likes to tell jokes. Now, with the persona of a comedian, instead of a
structured and formal answer, it gives a short paragraph that sounds more casual. Now, I'll admit
that I was hoping that it would tell a joke based on the prompt, what's the difference between a
shih tzu and a Havanese dog. If giving a persona isn't enough, you can give it explicit instructions
to tell a joke. And you can also try something else. You can give it examples of prompts and
completions to show it how you want to perform a task. So I give it a question, what's the
difference between a guitar and a fish? And I also give it the answer, which is a joke, you can't
tune a fish. And then I give it another example of the question, what's the difference between a
well-dressed dog on a bicycle and a poorly dressed dog on a unicycle. And I also give it an answer,
which is a tire. And finally, I give it the question that I want it to answer, which is,
what is the difference between a Shih Tzu and a Havanese dog? This pattern of giving examples
of both the input and the desired output in a prompt is what researchers are calling
few-shot prompting. In contrast, if you don't give any examples and just give it a task,
This is called zero shot prompting.
Now, the classic way of doing few shot prompting is to give the examples and then the next question.
But in practice, you may find it more helpful to give a bit more instruction for what you're asking the chatbot to do.
So I'm also going to start this prompt with this instruction.
Study how these questions are answered.
And I'm also going to proceed the final question with the instruction.
Now answer the following question.
Let's try this out using Meta AI.
Okay, so it's okay, some answers are funnier than others,
but you can see that it's attempting to answer the question as if giving the punchline to a joke,
in a similar structure as the previous examples given in the prompt.
Maybe you can play around with your own prompt and see if you can get the model to tell some good jokes.
The next optional video will take a break from AI and discuss some interpretations of the expression
every cloud has a silver lining. After that, the next several videos will dive into the different
categories of tasks that you saw in the overview. See you in the next video, or the one after that.