If you baked a cake before serving it to your friends, you may want to test it out just to make sure it's okay.
Similarly with chatbots, you may want to test it out to make sure it's doing what you expect it to do before you rely on it.
I think we're going to need to take like four or five more takes of this.
Here's a web article about a kind of dog called a Shih Tzu.
What if you ask a chatbot to extract relevant text about this dog's appearance,
given the web link to this article?
Ideally, it would be helpful if the chatbot pulls direct word-for-word quotes from the article
so that you can, for instance, cite the original source when writing an essay about dogs.
Let's try this out and see what happens.
At first glance, it looks like it's extracted direct quotes.
But let's just check this.
I'll look for some keywords that I can search for inside the web article itself.
For instance, I'll look for the phrase double-layered.
Back in the web article, I'm searching for the word double, and I don't find double-layered.
The closest I find is double-coat.
Let me go back to the chatbot's output and check for another word.
It describes the eyes of this dog as almond-shaped.
So I'll look for the word almond in the original article to check if it's quoting directly from the article.
In the original source, I'm searching for the word almond, and this word doesn't actually appear in the article at all.
So is the chatbot doing what I asked it to do in this case? Not quite.
Even though the chatbot responds that here's the relevant text extracted from this article, it looks like it's not actually doing that.
It's possibly paraphrasing this article or using its own knowledge to generate its output.
Let's try another chatbot host. You can use the Hugging Chat website and also choose Meta's
Llama model. Hugging Chat also lets you choose some options. One is Fetch URL and the other is
Web Search. The one I really want to be using here is Fetch URL because it's going to look at a
specific web page that I'm specifying with a web link. I'll go ahead and give it the same prompt
And when I run this, notice that it shows this message, called tool fetch URL.
You'll learn more about tools later in this course, but this message indicates that Hugging
Chat is going to the web link that I gave in the prompt and is reading through the text
on that site in order to perform the task that I requested.
Now the chatbot's output says, here is the relevant text, and it also outputs a paragraph
of text surrounded by quotation marks.
You can check some keywords to see if these are coming from the original article.
For instance, I will check if owlhead appears in the original article.
And it looks like it does.
Next, I can check if double coat is a phrase in the original article.
And it is.
So is the chatbot doing what I asked it to do?
In this case, yes, it looks like it is.
So it helps to keep in mind that before you trust the chatbot to perform a kind of task,
it might help to first give it a slightly simpler version of that task that's easy enough for you to
check and verify first. Just because a chatbot says that it's performing a task that you requested
doesn't necessarily mean that it's doing so correctly. Coming up next, you'll get an overview
of general tips for how to write your prompts that you can apply to all the use cases that
you'll see in the rest of the course. Let's check that out next.