You may have heard the expression "every cloud has a silver lining".
Let's take a look at what that means and also what it doesn't mean.
From a distance, this piece of artwork looks like a cloud.
But if you change your perspective a little bit
and take a close look, it looks like it's actually made up of many silver lines.
cool huh? This reminds me of a common expression, every cloud has a silver lining. People use this
saying to cheer up someone when something bad happens, and to tell them that maybe something
good comes out of something bad. Let's take a look at what this is, and also what it's not.
Let's motivate this with an example. Say you have a friend named Steve. He started his own company,
a fruit company, and he put a lot of work into this business. Unfortunately, one day, he was fired
from his job of running that fruit company. So he's really sad now, and you may be wondering what
you can do to help. Well, first, you may want to give Steve the space to acknowledge and feel those
sad emotions. You may recall experiencing similar emotions at some point in your life. Maybe you
applied to a job that you really liked, but you didn't get it. Or maybe you tried out for a dance
team and didn't make it into the team. So you may recall feeling sad, stressed, maybe even angry or
scared because of the uncertainty of what your future will look like. At this point, it's important
to acknowledge that it's okay to feel these emotions. And when your friend is going through
that situation, it's also important to let them know that it's okay for them to feel and express
their emotions. In psychology, this is called emotional validation. There's also an alternative
and somewhat instinctive urge to do something different, which is to try and fix things by
telling your friend, look on the bright side, or you should appreciate all the things that you have,
or maybe even saying you're better off this way. Even if this is coming out of good intentions,
the issue with saying these things is that it doesn't allow your friend to first feel their
emotions and doesn't let you demonstrate that you acknowledge and see that your friend is going
through a really difficult situation. In psychology, this is called toxic positivity in that it's
attempting to get someone to think positive without first acknowledging the real negatives
that they're going through. So there's a fine line. When you say every cloud has a silver lining,
you also want to acknowledge that the cloud is there too, that something bad happened. And you
want to give your friend that space to acknowledge that too. After that, you can start thinking about
the silver lining part. So why is it that sometimes when people look back on a difficult situation,
they actually think that situation turned out to be a good thing. Well, one reason is time. We all
have a limited amount of time in a day to pursue a job, project, or hobby. Sometimes when you get
turned down for a job or turned down for an opportunity to participate in a project, it means
that you now have the time and energy to devote to some other job or some other hobby or project.
Another reason why being rejected from your existing job or team could be a silver lining
is a change in your environment. You may really like your current environment, the people,
and the projects. But if you're forced to step out of that environment, such as take a new job,
or move to a new city, or join a new group of teammates, you may leave yourself open to new
opportunities that exist in that different environment. A related saying is, when one door
closes, another door opens. In economics, there's a related concept called opportunity cost. It says
that the job you have now has a cost associated with it because it's the cost of not having the
time and energy to devote to some other job or project. Let's hear from Steve in his own words
as he looks back at that moment when he was fired from his own company. I didn't see it then,
but it turned out that getting fired from Apple was the best thing that could have ever happened
to me. The heaviness of being successful was replaced by the lightness of being a beginner
again, less sure about everything. It freed me to enter one of the most creative periods of my life.
For some context, after Steve was fired from his own company, he went on to found other companies,
one called Next, another called Pixar. When Next was acquired by his original company,
Steve actually returned back to his original company, Apple.
And that's Steve. Coming up next, you'll get to practice various ways that you can use chatbots.
For this next set of videos, feel free to skip around and pick and choose which task
looks interesting to you or is most relevant to you at the moment.
The next video will be on the expand task.
Hope to see you there!