Sometimes you may be having a conversation with your friend when you realize that you
had something to add to a prior conversation, so then you go back to talking about that.
Chatbots can also sometimes refer to previous conversations as well, because they have some
additional code built around them called memory. Let's see how memory of prior conversations
affects how chatbots answer your most recent question. I'm going to ask a chatbot two questions
First, I'll ask "Who is Steve Jobs?" and it will reply.
Then I will ask it "Who is Eddie Xu?"
I'll use LM Studio and download a model from Mistral AI.
Let's see what it says.
And don't worry if you can't read all the text, I'll show you the relevant highlights
of the output in a moment.
So here's a review of what just happened.
In response to "Who is Steve Jobs?" the model replied that Steve Jobs is an entrepreneur
and gave more details about Steve Jobs' life and work in technology.
Then, in response to, who is Eddie Xu, it replied that Eddie Xu is an entrepreneur,
and mentions several other things, none of which are true,
but the point here is that they're all about engineering and business.
So next, I'm going to start a new conversation with the same model.
I'll ask it, who is Taylor Swift?
Then, after it responds, I'll ask it, who is Eddie Xu?
I'll use the same model, and I'll mention that before this, I started a new conversation by
clicking the new chat button on the top left corner. Let's see what happens, and then let's
review the results. So in response to Who is Taylor Swift, the model replies that Taylor Swift
is a singer-songwriter and mentions her life and work in music. Then, in response to Who is Eddie
Xu, it replies that Eddie is a violinist, composer, and conductor. Again, not true, but the point is
that the reply is all about music. So what's going on here? To understand why this is happening,
let's look at a feature of chatbots called memory. If you give a prompt like who is Steve Jobs and
the large language model gives its completion, a piece of software saves both your prompt and the
model's completion as part of an ongoing conversation. So when you give it another prompt, such as who is
Eddie Xu, that's not the only thing that gets sent to the large language model. This current prompt
gets appended to the ongoing conversation, and this whole conversation becomes the actual input
that's sent to the model, and that determines the model's completion. So if the earlier conversation
mentions entrepreneur, then the current completion may be influenced by this prior conversation,
and also mention entrepreneur. This feature of chatbots, which records the ongoing conversation
history and feeds it to the large language model is a feature that we call the memory of a chatbot.
And I'd just like to point out that the memory is a piece of software that is built independently
of the large language model itself. The model itself will not actually remember any of your
prior prompts or its prior completions in an ongoing conversation. Same thing happens when
you first ask, who is Taylor Swift? That prompt and its completion gets saved into memory. The
to that conversation, and the model uses that entire conversation about singer-songwriter
and music to determine its current completion, which ends up also talking about music.
And the influence of the conversation history may show up in less obvious situations as
this.
For instance, I was using Meta AI inside WhatsApp and asked it a few questions about the Olympics.
Then I asked it, who is Eddie Xu?
It replied that Eddie is a table tennis player who attended the Olympics.
Again, this is a hallucination, but the point is that it hallucinated about the Olympics
because the previous conversation history was about that same topic.
Now this has implications because you might be using the chatbot for an extended period
of time and for different tasks, and the completions that the chatbot gives you may start to be
influenced by previous conversations that you don't expect to be related to what you
are currently asking about in your most recent prompt.
For example, maybe an earlier conversation mentions pineapples.
Then, when you ask for pizza topping recommendations, it might suggest pineapples in part because
it was influenced by the previous conversation.
So I recommend that you start a new conversation whenever you want to move on to a new topic
to clear out any previous prompts and completions that might affect the current completion.
So the model's completion will be based on your current prompt and not any past prompts
and completions.
So if you ask for pizza topping recommendations, it won't necessarily be influenced to suggest
pineapples.
Most chatbots let you click on a button to start a new conversation or a new chat.
This clears out the memory of the previous conversations.
I would like to add one more thing about why memory is a separate piece of software that's
distinct from the actual large language model itself.
When a model is done training, the parameters in the model will no longer be updated when
is being used by end users like you and me. So when you send a prompt to a large language model
and it gives its completion, the parameters in that model will not be affected or changed by
receiving your prompt. What will change is the memory, which takes in the completion, appends
that to the conversation history, and also takes in the next prompt so that it can send the
conversation history and the current prompt to the large language model. For practical reasons,
it would be really difficult for any company that's hosting a large language model to try
and modify the parameters of a model based on each user's input to that model. And it probably
wouldn't be something you'd want anyways, because if a shared model changes its parameters after each
interaction with its users, then some other users' conversations with the chatbot would then affect
your own interactions with that same chatbot. So if one person is talking to the chatbot about
pineapples and you ask the chatbot for pizza topping recommendations, it might recommend pineapples.
But the way chatbots are designed, the memory of a chatbot is specific to you, the user,
even though the large language model is shared among many users.
So if someone is talking to a chatbot about pineapples,
and you ask the same chatbot to recommend pizza toppings,
its response won't be influenced by the other person's conversations about pineapples.
Next up, some tasks are easier, and some tasks are harder for a large language model to get right.
Let's look at the level of difficulty of various tasks next.