In addition to transforming your text from one language to another, you can also transform it
by rewording it or revising it. Let's take a look at how you can use chatbots to do that.
Let's say you recently became friends with a captain of a ship because he very generously gave
you a ride home on a ship when you were in Puerto Rico. Your friend arrived here recently after
sailing through a hurricane around Bermuda in the Atlantic Ocean. He recently bought a compass in
Miami, Florida, and he wants to ask customer service if he can return it. So he's written a letter to
customer service asking for a replacement, and he's asking you to help reword his email to make sure
it's understood. Well, you can use a chatbot to help you reword your friend's email. Here are some
instructions to revise the following text to American-style English and to choose accessible
vocabulary words. To increase the chance that customer service is willing to help out, you ask
a chatbot to adjust the tone to keep it positive and avoid any misunderstanding. You also ask it to
try its best to maintain the original intent of the text. So let's try it out.
So it looks like the chatbot maintains the original intent by pointing out that the compass
isn't functioning and that your friend feels disappointed and even mentions trying to fix it
by giving it a friendly gesture. And the chatbot still says that your friend is hoping for a prompt
resolution and it signs the name Francis K.O. Ko. So it looks like it's doing a decent job of
rewording it while maintaining the original intent. And this can be helpful to you as well if you're
traveling abroad and learning another language, maybe even trying to work in another language.
You can ask a chatbot to help you reword your letters or emails or any writing that you do in
language that you're still learning. And even if you're writing in a language of your choice,
you might find it helpful to use speech recognition, also called voice dictation,
to help you with your writing. What you'll find when you're using speech recognition
is that the final wording might need a little bit of cleanup. This is in part because when you speak,
you're also thinking through the words you want to use. Maybe you'll also use some filler words
or repeat some phrase to try to clarify what you wanted to say. So let's look at an example and see
how you can ask a chatbot to help you clean up the transcription for you.
So, you know, I explained to all the people that, you know, that were there about how,
you know, I guess sausages are made. And so, well, well, that was the last time they invited
me back to the hot dog eating contest. Let's see how you can ask a chatbot to help clean up this
transcription. Let's first point out that the text that you want to work on was produced from speech
recognition, and you can ask the chatbot to rewrite it to correct the spelling or wording that may be
due to converting speech to text. For example, there may be words that sound the same but are
spelled differently and have different meanings, which you might recall from earlier in the course.
There are also filler words that we naturally may say when we're speaking aloud or thinking aloud,
but maybe we want to remove those in the final transcript. And this next part I think is quite
helpful because sometimes when a chatbot revises my writing, it may do more than I actually wanted
to do. So I want to set expectations that what I'm looking for is to preserve as much as possible
the style and tone and word choice. Again, this goes back to a general prompting tip of setting
expectations for what you consider to be a good output or a good outcome. So let's see how it does.
It gives the revision as well as some explanations for what it changed, and I like that it seems to be keeping most of the word choice that I originally had.
It also explains when it's removing filler words and phrases that are unclear or not grammatically correct.
You can also ask a chatbot to help you rewrite a prompt.
For example, maybe you want to translate Every Cloud Has a Silver Lining into other languages.
You can first ask the chatbot to rewrite the prompt to make the instructions clear and to get more complete or thorough results.
Let's see what we get from that.
So it's pretty good.
First, it puts quotes around the phrase, every cloud has a silver lining.
It also specifies specific languages, but it also asks in the prompt to not limit the answer to just those languages.
It also asks the chatbot to ensure that the translations convey the same meaning as the original phrase,
So this is getting into whether it would be a figurative idiomatic type of translation
or a literal word-for-word translation.
So it's pretty cool.
Looks like even if you forget most of the tips and tricks that you learned in this course,
you can still remember to ask a chatbot to help you reword and rewrite your prompts.
But I hope you still found all the advice on prompting helpful, and I hope you also had
fun while learning it.
Coming up next, you'll practice asking a chatbot to help you with fact-checking.
Let's look at that in the next video.