So far, you've been inputting text and getting text as output, or sometimes images.
Now let's see how you can input both images and text at the same time as your prompt.
Normally, when you have an app that is able to handle more than one kind of input, such as images and text,
behind the scenes, it's actually a combination of models.
So the image may get sent to a specific model, an image captioning model, that takes an image as input and outputs text that describes that image.
For example, it might output the text, a pineapple cake.
Then, this caption, as well as the text of the prompt, which was, how do I make something like this?
These both get sent to a large language model, which can then output a completion, such as, here's how to make a pineapple cake.
More recently, some models have been trained to directly take in both an image and text as the
prompt, and then be able to output completion directly. These have been called large multimodal
models, or LMMs, or simply multimodal models. And these large multimodal models are what you'll be
practicing with here. So what can you do now that you can also input images and text? Well, if you
If you think back to all the other tasks that you've practiced: expand, synthesize, transform,
evaluate, chat, and take actions, for all those scenarios, you can input both images and text
as a prompt.
A natural situation where you would input images is if you're using your phone to take a picture
of something that you see and ask a chatbot to do something with it.
So I'm going to demonstrate these tasks using chatbots that you can access as apps on your
phone.
the expand task which includes answering questions. As you've seen with just pure text, I recommend
that you first ask the chatbot to describe the image or write out any relevant information and
then ask it to perform the task that you want. So I've taken an image of a piece of food and I'm
asking it "what is this? How do I make it?" and it responds that this is a Taiwanese pineapple cake
and then follows with baking instructions for how to make it. Just as you saw with machine
In translation, the context may affect how the model performs.
In this case, the context may be the background of the object that you're interested in.
Notice that whereas earlier I placed this food on top of some white paper towels, now
I've placed it on top of a bluish-gray plate.
So now when I ask it "What is this?" and "How do I make it?" it replies that this
is an Indian sweet called "son papadi".
If I try again, now it says that this is an Indian sweet called "Gajou Kotli".
So just to better understand what's going on, I can go back to that original earlier
image where I placed this food on top of a white paper towel.
Then I'll ask "What is this and how do I make it?"
Then it says "This appears to be a Taiwanese pineapple cake".
And I was going to experiment more with other plates or backgrounds, but I got hungry.
You can also ask a multimodal chatbot to give you ideas for how to interpret a painting
even how to name it. Here I'm uploading a painting that I've made, followed by some
text, describe this artwork, and suggest what this artwork is about, then suggest possible
names to give it. So it's pretty cool that it recognizes that this painting is based
on Vincent van Gogh's Starry Night painting. It also acknowledges the unusual addition
of the green frog. It provides possible ways to interpret the painting, such as "a child's
view of the world". Finally, it suggests some possible names for the painting, such as "Twinkle
little frog. And you can have a chatbot assist you with synthesizing visual
information around you. For instance, based on the rules seen in this photo, can I
park here?
Here the chatbot is requesting additional information from me because
it points out that whether I can park here or not depends on the day of the
week and time of day, as well as whether I have a special permit. So I'll give this
additional information. Today is Friday 5:00 p.m. and I don't have special
permits. Can I park here?
And it tells me that the answer is yes and also provides details to explain why.
And to be honest, I have in fact checked this because these signs are really hard
to read. If you want to analyze those parking sign rules, please let me know if
the chatbot was correct. You saw earlier in the course that with optical
character recognition you can apply translation to an image, for example a
a picture of a restaurant menu. You can also use a multimodal chatbot to transform text into
another language. And the nice thing is, on top of that, you can also ask it to perform
follow-up tasks, such as describing each food item.
So notice that in addition to translating each food item, it also shows the original language,
which would help me point to what I want when I'm in the restaurant communicating with the
restaurant server. It also provides a brief description of the food, which can help me
me decide what to order.
Here's an example of how you can apply evaluation.
Describe criteria for evaluating photographs.
Then evaluate the quality of these photographs and assign a numeric score.
So I've uploaded three photographs that I took in a garden.
The chatbot first provides some criteria that it would use for evaluating these photographs.
And for each photograph, it assigns a numeric score, explains why it gave that score, and
it also describes what kind of flowers these are.
In this case, these are dahlias.
And you can also chat with a multimodal chatbot about some photograph you took, as well as
ask it to take some action, like search the web for you.
Here's a picture of a sign of a park in Montreal, Canada.
I'll ask it, "Where should I visit first?"
It recognizes the location that this sign is about and suggests some places within the
It also continues the conversation by asking me if I have any specific interests to help
it better understand what I should do next.
I reply that I like taking pictures, so it does some web searches and provides more suggestions
for places I can visit and take photographs.
Coming up next, you probably heard terms like "generative AI" and "transformers".
Now that you've had some hands-on practice with these AI models, let's look at some common
vocabulary words that may come up when you're reading about or hearing about AI.