*music*
Chatbots can also be used for evaluation.
For example, you can use the chatbot to help with fact checking.
Imagine this scenario:
You're writing to your friend on their birthday
about their birthday cake that you bought for them.
Here's what you plan to say:
I dropped your birthday cake on the ground,
but don't worry, I picked it up right away.
So according to the 5-second rule,
the bacteria didn't have enough time to crawl on the cake.
Happy birthday!
Just in case, you ask a chatbot to evaluate this and check if it's correct before you
send it.
So it looks like it helped fix some grammar and spelling issues.
Okay, not bad.
But that's more of a rewording and revising task.
It's not evaluating the content of the written text.
Let's get a second opinion.
So in this case, this chatbot is checking the factual accuracy of the writing.
It's pointing out that the 5 second rule is a common myth, and also points out that
the cake isn't necessarily free of bacteria. So that's pretty helpful to know. And just to make
it clear that you're asking a chatbot to fact check as opposed to checking wording or grammar,
you can ask, is this factually correct? And then you can give it the text that you want it to check.
Let's go back to the earlier chatbot that had fixed the wording instead of fact checking. And now
it's also pointing out that this five second rule is a myth. And you can ask a chatbot to fact check
itself by asking it if it's sure of its previous output. You may recall this logic problem from
earlier in the course. After the chatbot gives its answer, you can ask a follow-up question. Can you
check your response to see if it is correct? And you may recall that this follow-up question is
called reflection, as you're asking the chatbot to reflect on its earlier output. So as you saw
before, the chatbot answers yes, which is incorrect. Now let's ask the follow-up question to check if
previous response was correct. And now, given a chance to reflect on its previous answer
and reasoning, the chatbot corrects itself and also explains its answer.
So not only is it helpful for you as a human to fact check a chatbot and its output,
the nice thing is you can also ask a chatbot to help fact check other pieces of writing as well.
And maybe the next time you ask a chatbot to perform a task, you can also ask it to reflect
on its output and check if it's correct. Next, another way a chatbot can evaluate is by grading.
And by that I mean check if a student's answer to a problem is correct or not.
Let's take a look at grading next.