Have you ever had to read through a really long document and summarize the key points?
Well, now you can ask a chatbot to do that for you.
Now let's take a look at one of these synthesized tasks called summarization.
Text summarization can really help you speed up your learning or help you when you're researching
a topic to really extract the parts of an article or document that's most relevant to what you're
looking for.
So let's look at an example where you might use summarization.
Let's say you want to learn about Banksy from a Wikipedia article.
It's quite long, and you may want to focus on a specific subtopic within the article.
So how can you ask a chatbot to help?
One thing you can try is to give the chatbot a web link and then ask it to summarize the article.
And in this case, I'm going to have it focus on a specific subtopic,
which is to summarize Banksy's activities that relate to social, geopolitical, or current events.
Let's use Notebook LM by Google, which is a tool that lets you upload documents and then chat about them using Gemini.
You can start by clicking the button "Create" and you can see there are a couple options for uploading documents.
You can connect it to Google Drive, you can paste the text in directly, you can upload documents in PDF or text format,
and it also has the option for you to provide a link to a website. Let's use the website option.
Again, here's the Wikipedia article, so you can copy the web link and paste it in here.
I'm fast forwarding a bit, but it takes a few seconds to process the website.
Now you can see on the left that it has uploaded this web article as a source
that the chatbot will use when you prompt it for something.
And here's the prompt: Summarize Banksy's activities that relate to social, geopolitical,
or current events. Let's zoom in a bit. You can see that it's a fairly detailed and also
annotated list of topics. You can double check that these are coming from the source material.
It mentions an elephant that was painted pink.
If you go back to the web article, you can verify that it's mentioned there.
You can also click on the citation buttons within the output,
and it opens up a side window that also shows the original text from the Wikipedia article.
Let's do another check.
It mentions a piece of art called Love is in the Bin.
Here, if you click on the first citation, it doesn't seem to mention this piece of art.
But for the next citation, it does mention this particular piece of artwork.
And if you go to the original article, you can see it there too.
So I hope you can see that having a chatbot read through an article first
can really help you zoom in and focus on the topics or details that you're really interested in.
And I hope you can also see how valuable it is to be able to reference the original source material.
And I'll just mention that Balloon Girl is one of Banksy's most famous pieces of art,
and it was transformed into another piece of art called Love is in the Bin.
If you're curious to learn more, you can check out the Wikipedia article or ask a chatbot.
You may find that if you use the keyword summarize for a task,
then a chatbot may reply in its own words instead of providing direct quotes from the original source material.
And since not all chatbots have the feature of linking citations to the original source,
it may become a bit more difficult to verify if the chatbot's output is coming from the source document.
so you may prefer that it gives you word-for-word text from the source instead.
One recommendation I have is, instead of saying summarize,
you may want to ask it to extract relevant text as direct quotes.
This encourages the chatbot to use the exact wording from the source material.
One thing I've experienced is that sometimes it's not enough to only say extract relevant text.
Sometimes it works better if you use this entire phrase, extract relevant text as direct quotes.
to try to make it clear as possible that you want it to not try to summarize in its own words,
but to really get the original wording from the source.
Let's try this out with ChatGPT.
And it looks like it has provided some direct quotes, but let's double check.
So as before, you can copy some text and then search for it in the original source.
Here you can see the issue is just that the elephant in the room was in double quotes in the original article,
and it was changed to single quotes in the output of the chatbot,
but the rest of the text was retrieved word for word.
Let's check another example.
Here's another piece of text, nine images on the Israeli West Bank wall,
and we can see that it's extracted that text word for word.
One thing I would like to note is that if I run this multiple times,
sometimes ChatGPT will say,
sorry, I actually can't do that.
Please go to the website yourself and extract the relevant text.
So sometimes when you ask it to extract direct quotes,
it might decline to do so. For other chatbots that I've tried, a lot of them are only allowed
to summarize, but are not allowed to extract direct quotes. And most of the chatbots that
you've seen in the previous videos do not have the ability to work with a web link.
Sometimes they will reply as if they're complying with your instruction, but when you double check,
you'll notice that it's just producing information based on its own knowledge and not retrieving it
from the article. So if providing a direct web link to a website isn't working, then one thing
you can try is to download that web page as an HTML file and upload the file to
the chatbot. So then the prompt will become: "From the following attached
document, extract all the relevant text and the rest of the prompt is the same."
For ChatGPT, there's this paperclip icon and it allows you to upload from your
computer. So let's first go back to the Wikipedia article and download it as a
file and then let's save the web page as HTML only.
Now that you have a file, you can upload it and then give your instructions.
And you can see that it has these hyperlinks in green that refer to the attached file.
It's saying, "These are quotes that were extracted directly from the attached document."
And it's always good to double-check, so you can copy some text from this output
and then check if it's actually in the original article.
For Claude, you can see that you can upload five files with a limit of 30 megabytes each.
So I can upload this HTML file to see if it works.
works. And here it says that it's over the length limit. So all of these chatbots have
different context lengths. That's how much text it can take in at one single time as
a prompt. Let's try this with Command + R + by Coher. We'll upload that same HTML file.
OK, so far, no error, so I'll go ahead and give it the instructions. So this is taking
a bit of time, so I'm speeding up the video recording a bit. One of the reasons this takes
quite a long time is because the HTML file has a lot of other structure around the text.
Later, you'll see a way to make this a bit more efficient for the chatbot by just giving
it the exact text and nothing else.
But you can see that if you were to open up the HTML file, there's a lot of structure
around the text that gives it the font and also the layout.
If you were to look at this from a text document, it would sort of look like code.
So coming back, looks like it was able to process this document.
And what's really cool is that chatbots can understand that when you ask for social, political,
cultural, or current events, you can see topics about poverty or environment and understand
that these words are also related to what you're asking for. In comparison, if you were to use
traditional software, you would probably have to specify keywords that you were looking for
that refer to these social, political, or current events,
such as specific names of countries
and specific keywords like climate or war or refugee.
And it's still really helpful to be ready
to copy and paste the source text directly into the prompt.
This is because some chatbots don't take in HTML files.
Some chatbots also don't take in any attached documents at all,
but they can still perform the task quite well
if you give them the source document
as plain text inside the prompt.
So I recommend first saving that text into some word processor like Google Docs or Microsoft Word,
and also first checking how much text the chatbot can actually take in as an input at one time.
Let's check if the other chatbots let you upload documents.
In Mistral, there's currently no upload file feature at the time that I'm filming this lecture.
In Gemini, you can only upload an image. We'll get into images later in the course.
In Meta AI, you can't currently upload anything at this time.
And in Microsoft Copilot, you can only upload an image.
So for these chatbots, you can still copy and paste the text directly into the prompt.
To make it easier, let's first copy this text into a word processor.
So you can open up a blank Google Doc, for instance,
use the keyboard shortcut Ctrl-A on a PC or Command-A on a Mac,
copy all the text, and paste it into the word processor.
Let's do a little bit of cleanup.
Usually at the bottom of these Wikipedia articles, there are citations and external links.
We probably won't need these for this task, so I'm just going to make it a bit shorter
by removing all the references.
And I'll also do a little bit of cleanup at the top.
Now you can double check if you can actually paste all the text directly into these chatbots,
because they do have a limit to how much text they can take in for the prompt.
And again, this is called the context length.
So let's see how much text can fit into each of these chatbots as a single prompt.
Recall that prompting tip test it before you rely on it.
So you can check what was the last piece of text that still appears inside the prompt window after you try to paste in the entire text.
For Mistral, it looks like it was able to take in the entire text that I copied from the doc.
With Gemini, it looks like it stopped somewhere earlier, and I can check by copying some of the text and seeing where in the document that is.
So at about page 26, it stopped pasting in the text.
So with Gemini, it was able to take in about 26 pages worth of the text.
With Mistral, the whole thing was about 51 pages.
Now let's check the context length for Meta AI.
Looks like it was about 14 pages.
Now let's try Microsoft Copilot.
It says maximum character limit reached, and I can see where that ended in the document.
And in this case, it was about 4 pages.
Now let's prepare to put the entire text about Banksy into the prompt.
And then after that, I'm going to say, for the provided text above, extract all the relevant text as direct quotes, so it's the same request as before.
Notice that I'm putting a delimiter here to separate the article text from the instructions.
These characters are called backticks, but you could also use three hashtags or three double quotes or three single quotes.
And if you want to use three of any other characters, it'll probably work okay as well.
Let's try this with Mistral, since I was able to fit the entire source text into the context window.
Let's also try this with Claude. Recall that when I uploaded the HTML file directly to Claude,
it said that it was over the context length window. Now, I'm just copy-pasting that text
from the word processor. It saves that text as an attachment, and it looks like it can take in that
entire 52 pages of text. So this is good to keep in mind, that if you upload an HTML file, the extra
formatting also takes up space in the context window. If you want to make the most of the context
window, then paste in pure text. And I encourage you to try this out yourself on your own article
of interest and ask it to summarize or extract relevant text to help you understand a particular
subtopic that you're interested in. And just one quick reminder about privacy that you'll probably
want to just paste in something that's publicly available and not some personal document or
proprietary document. If you want more privacy, then I recommend working with a downloadable model.
Another way to synthesize information is to give it labels, such as topics or positive or negative sentiment, and more.
This is helpful when you have a lot of separate pieces of text that you want to make sense of.
Let's look at labeling text next.