You've probably used chatbots in the same way that you use web search, by asking it a question and getting an answer.
This is an example of an expand task in that you give it a small input, such as, who is Taylor Swift, and you get a lot of information back.
Let's take a look at how you can use chatbots for question answering.
Let's look at various ways that you can ask for information from a chatbot.
We can start with asking a question such as "What is K-pop and hip-hop?"
Let's see what the chatbot says.
Beyond asking a question, you can also request information with explicit instructions.
For example, you can say "Compare and contrast" or "List" or "Describe" or "Explain".
And you can give your prompt more structure with a sequence of subtasks.
For example, list some resources, then collect key information like persons and terminology,
then list out similarities, and then list out differences, and finally draw some conclusions.
So it's nice that when you give your prompt more structure and also flesh out what you're looking
for, it also will prompt the chatbot to follow your structure and also provide more information
that you're asking for. And you can ask follow-up questions or add follow-up instructions. For
example, for the previous two topics, divide your analysis into two parts. Compare and contrast the
music, and then compare and contrast the dance style. Notice that you could have also included
this in the previous prompt so that it's just one long prompt. But sometimes you may get better
results if you break up your task into separate prompts. If you ask a chatbot to do too many
things, it may not do all of them that well compared to if it was able to focus on fewer
tasks at the same time. And let's see what it says.
And you can ask it to review its previous work. Sometimes it can spot its own mistakes
if you just ask it to double check. People have been calling this prompting technique
reflection because the model is asked to reflect on its previous completions to check if they can
be improved or corrected. So for instance, you can ask it to check for factual accuracy
and also ask it to add any additional information. Asking a chatbot to review its work can make a
difference because once a chatbot predicts a word, it only moves onto the next word and the next and
can't go back to change or remove any word that it's already output. And to make it easier to see
what it decided to revise, I'll ask it to copy over its original output that it reviewed,
followed by the clarification or addition. I'm calling these key and value because that's a
common way that software engineers like to organize information. If you're not familiar with key-value
pairs, don't worry, you can write your prompt without explicitly using these vocabulary words
and it will probably still work. And let's see what it says.
You can go deeper into subtopics based on what you learned from its previous completions.
For instance, I can say, you mentioned breaking, breakdancing. Can you clarify what this is?
You can think of this as just asking another follow-up question, but I'd like to mention this because you may sometimes feel like a chatbot's answer didn't give you the depth of information that you were looking for when you first asked for it.
But if you focus on a narrower subtopic, you may get more details than you did in the first more general request.
And so I'll actually ask two follow-up questions.
The second one will be, what is the difference between breaking and breakdancing?
So the first question is, I'll ask it to clarify breaking or breakdancing.
And then my next follow-up is, what's the difference between breaking and breakdancing?
And so it clarifies that the preferred term is breaking as opposed to breakdancing.
So far, you've seen questions or instructions that ask about a keyword such as hip-hop or breaking.
What if instead you have a fuzzy recollection of a word or concept and need a reminder of what that is?
You can ask a chatbot to fill in the blanks for you.
For example, I'll ask it for words or terminology that describe this,
and then I'll describe what I'm thinking of as best I can.
someone sees their friends doing fun stuff on social media, and it makes them feel bad.
One thing I'd like to point out is I worded this so that I'm trying to encourage the chatbot to
give multiple suggestions for what this keyword or terminology could be by using the plural words
as opposed to singular word. Sometimes if I don't hint that I want multiple options,
it will just give me one result. Let's see if the chatbot can help me fill in the blanks.
So it looks like the word I was thinking of was FOMO, but it also lists other possible
words or phrases that I didn't think about and that I can ask follow-up questions about.
So it also mentions other things like social comparison and asks me if I want to learn
more, and I say yes.
And now it provides more detailed definitions of all those words it suggested, as well as
some strategies for coping with social media envy.
You can also interact with chatbots in a way that you probably wouldn't with a regular search engine.
You can try to clarify maybe some confusion about some topic.
For example, I wanted clarification on this.
When people announce some accomplishment, they either say they're proud of that accomplishment,
but other people say they're humbled by their accomplishment or award.
So my question is, do these mean the same thing?
And why do people say one versus the other?
Let's try this out.
So it defines proud of and it defines humbled by and tries to explain why people choose one or the
other based on personal preferences, culture, or situation. Now I've tried this with a couple
different chatbots and they all gave similar safe answers that are some version of, well,
it depends on the person or it depends on the culture. What I thought was interesting with this
answered by Claude was that it mentioned something that's kind of an opinion or maybe even an insight.
It says, it's worth noting that humbled by is sometimes criticized as false modesty. And so,
it's not necessarily that you have to believe what it's saying, but it's trying to provide some
additional opinion or insight that you might get when you're talking to a human. So it's helpful to
try out the same prompt or question or task on more than one chatbot. You might learn more than
if you just stuck with just one. Coming up next, you'll use chatbots to help you generate
new ideas. I'll see you in the next video.