You've seen how you as a person can chat with a chatbot.
Now let's see how you can have two chatbots chat with each other in order to collaborate on a task.
So far in the course, you've seen how you can collaborate with a chatbot where you give it guidance and feedback and ask it to iterate on some task.
But what if instead you ask another chatbot to play that role of giving guidance and feedback?
And you're still in the discussion more as an intermediary overseeing both of them.
Let's take an example where one of the chatbots is a writer for a news publication,
and the other chatbot is an editor who reviews the work of the writer and gives feedback and suggestions.
Here's the prompt for the writer to write their first draft.
You can start by giving the role.
So the writer chatbot is a professional magazine writer for the Daily Bugle.
They take an edgy, humorous approach to sharing serious matters to their readers.
And here is the task.
Write a short opinion piece to argue that superheroes should clean up after themselves
after saving the city, such as cleaning up spider webs.
Sign the essay with the title, Your Friendly Neighborhood Writer.
I'll go ahead and ask Coheres, Command R+, to play the role of the writer and give it
the role in his task.
And here's the output.
Don't worry, I'll scroll back up so that we can go through this together.
The article starts out with some praise for superheroes and then points out that they
need to start cleaning up after their battles.
It brings up cleanup costs and that taxpayers have to pay for them.
It does acknowledge the efforts of superheroes in saving the city,
but also points out that they could do a quick sweep and make the city look nice again.
And as instructed in the prompt, the writer chatbot signs the article,
Your Friendly Neighborhood Writer.
So overall, I think it does follow the role of trying to make this a humorous approach
to addressing a serious topic.
So a second chatbot will now play the role of the editor.
I'll start the prompt with the role and then follow up with the task for the first review of the essay.
So you're going to tell the second chatbot that they're an editor for a news organization, The Daily Bugle.
The editor ensures that articles are getting their facts right and citing sources.
The editor also encourages citing numbers and aggregate information to back up anecdotal evidence.
But they allow the journalist to maintain their writing style and artistic vision.
And here's the task.
Given an essay, give feedback on what is good and what can be improved.
Suggest additional examples that might fit in with the existing content.
Suggest phrases or wording that could make the essay more engaging.
Also, do not rewrite the essay.
And I mention this because sometimes when I've tried this, the editor chatbot will not only give feedback, but will then try to rewrite the entire essay.
But that role is for the writer chatbot.
Finally, we'll provide the essay at the bottom.
To play the role of the editor, I will use Mistral-Large2 by Mistral AI.
So I'll give it the prompt, then I'll go back to Command R plus and copy the essay.
And here's the output.
I'll scroll back up to the top once it's done.
Okay, so it looks like the editor breaks things down by what it likes and things that can be improved.
It likes the conversational tone and use of specific examples in arguing for superhero accountability.
For areas of improvement, the editor asks for facts and numbers,
for example, estimates of property damage caused by superhero battles.
Recall that it's probably taking a note from the role description in the prompt
where we ask the editor to have a preference for specific numbers and for citing sources.
The editor recommends some additional examples, which it will suggest below.
It also suggests providing a counter-argument or rebuttal to add to this essay.
And this is kind of interesting because psychologists have studied
what types of articles can be persuasive enough to convince someone to change their perspective.
on some topic about science or politics.
They actually found that articles which try to fairly address all the other options and
opinions and also provide evidence that might go even against the main argument, those articles
that seem more balanced have a slightly better chance of persuading someone to consider the
main argument and actually change their minds.
And here are some additional examples that the editor suggests could be added.
It mentions Iron Man's suit malfunctions, as well as Captain America's fights, and also
environmental impact of Thor's weather-related powers. The editor also suggests some specific
wording changes. Instead of, it's time for a little tough love, it recommends, it's time for a reality
check. Instead of, don't get me started on the cleanup costs, it recommends, let's not even broach
the topic of cleanup costs. It's enough to make a taxpayer's head spin. So some of these style
choices I wouldn't necessarily think are better than the original. They're not worse either, but it
helps for you as a human to stay in the loop to make that decision. The last suggestion is to say
we're not asking for the moon, just a little tidiness. So that's kind of a fun stylistic way
of saying we don't ask for much. The editor also recommends gathering interviews from eyewitnesses
or experts about the topic. Now let's bring this feedback back to the writer and now we'll ask the
writer to incorporate the feedback. Given the following feedback from the editor, consider what
feedback you, the writer, want to accept, but also consider what feedback that you as the writer will
reject and explain why. I think it's also important to give the writer some agency in deciding whether
they should accept or reject the feedback. Next, we can ask the writer to reflect on their essay
and share what they might want to change, and then finally they'll rewrite their essay. And below
these instructions, we'll go ahead and include the editor's feedback. So I'll give the writer this
prompt as well as copy and paste the feedback from the other chatbot. Okay, so scrolling back up,
Let's see what it says. The writer acknowledges the praise for their tone and use of specific
examples. It agrees that providing more factual data such as property damage estimates would be
helpful and acknowledges the additional examples. It also agrees about gathering insights from
eyewitnesses and experts. It's also rejecting some feedback, which I think is helpful because it's
not always the case that the editor is always right or that the writer is also always right.
So it's helpful to allow both the writer and the editor to play some role in deciding what goes in
and what goes out of this essay. In this case, the writer decides not to use a counter-argument or
rebuttal because it believes this may shift the tone and detract from the intended style,
which is a more light-hearted and humorous tone. I personally don't see how including counter-arguments
or differing points of view would prevent the essay from having a humorous light-hearted tone,
so this is still a reminder that you as the person, as the human, still play an important
role in deciding what makes sense here. And now the writer is rewriting its essay. Let's see if we can
spot how it has changed its writing based on the feedback. It's now using the phrase reality check,
which was one of these suggestions. It also includes the examples suggested about Iron Man,
Captain America, and Thor. It also used the suggested wording, we're not asking for the moon
here. It adds something new, which I think is kind of a nice touch. Those with extraordinary powers
also take on extraordinary responsibilities. If you're familiar with the Spider-Man comics or
movies, it's a rewording of a famous line from the Spider-Man comics, with great ability comes great
accountability, or something like that. Maybe you can ask the chatbot what that famous phrase is.
All right, let's do this one last time. I mean, I could do this all day. But let's wrap up with a
second review by the editor. Now you're going to ask the editor to review the second draft.
Discuss which of the editor's suggestions were actually incorporated in the writer's second
draft, and also which suggestions were not. Then think through whether the essay is ready for
publication, but also think through reasons why the essay should go through more revisions. Finally,
ask the editor to decide whether the essay is ready for publication or if it should go through
more revisions. So we'll give these instructions to do the second review, and here's the output.
Once it's done, we'll scroll back up and go through this. The editor notes about how some of their
suggestions about adding examples of Iron Man and Captain America were included. They also point
out that some of the phrasing was included, such as reality check and making a taxpayer's headspin.
It also found that its mention of the environmental impact was also included. The editor also notes
some things that were not included, such as more factual data or estimates of property damage,
or additional eyewitness or expert accounts. It notes that there was no counter-argument or
rebuttal, although they acknowledged that the writer made this conscious decision not to include that.
It lists out possible reasons for allowing the essay to be published as is, and then reasons why it may benefit from additional revisions.
Notice that it points out two areas where the writer did not add these suggestions, but also did not explicitly reject them.
In fact, the writer, if you recall, actually thought these were good suggestions.
For example, the writer did not, in the second draft, add additional statistics or eyewitness or expert accounts.
So it looks like the editor makes the decision that the article should go through another round of revision before publication.
At this point, I do want to point out your role as a human in all of this, because it
can kind of feel like you can just find some quick way of automating this so that the writer
and editor chatbots talk to each other directly, and you can just wait for them to give the
final results.
And there are tools that allow you to do that, but here's one example that I think makes
the case for why having you as a human in the loop is so valuable.
When the writer is incorporating feedback in its second draft, it likes the recommendation
given by the editor to gather insights from eyewitnesses or experts. So it says,
I will create fictional quotes or interviews to provide a unique and entertaining perspective.
Now for a human, this may ring alarm bells right away because a publication, any news organization,
should publish facts and not make things up. Let's check how the editor followed up during
this second review. It mentions that there are no insights from eyewitnesses or experts added,
which could have provided a unique and entertaining perspective. And while that's true, it would have
been even better if the editor realized the bigger issue, which is that the role of the news
organization is to provide facts and not to make things up. So having a human in the loop, having
you in the loop when working with AI, applies pretty much any time you're working with software
that helps you automate things. It's especially the case when the task requires an ability to handle ambiguity and to possibly think more broadly,
as is the case with using chatbots to perform these more open-ended tasks.
Coming up, chatbots can output text to perform lots of different tasks, but if you give them tools to use, they can take actions beyond just outputting text.
Let's look at taking action using tools next.