You're probably familiar with personal assistants on a smartphone, computer, or home device,
such as Apple's Siri or Google's Personal Assistant or Amazon Alexa.
These don't necessarily need powerful large language models to perform simple tasks,
but they combine speech recognition with language models,
as well as tools to allow you to interact with apps using just your voice.
Let's go over a few ways that you might use a personal assistant on your phone.
I'll be using Google Personal Assistant to demonstrate these.
If you happen to have an Android phone sitting near you, I recommend putting it a bit further
away from you so that this video lecture doesn't accidentally activate your own phone's personal
assistant.
So here's an example of how you can check your calendar and add a new event to your calendar.
Hey Google, what are my calendar events for tomorrow?
There are five entries tomorrow.
First up, you have breakfast at Tiffany's at 8 a.m.
Here's the rest.
Add a new calendar event for tomorrow from 3 p.m. to 5.30 p.m.
What's the title of the event?
Practice juggling.
Okay, practice juggling tomorrow from 3 p.m. to 5.30 p.m.
Do you want to save that?
Yes.
Sure, I added it.
Hey Google, open up my calendar to tomorrow.
There are six entries for tomorrow.
First up, you have breakfast at Tiffany's at 8am.
Here's the rest.
And here's how you might send and edit a text message to a friend.
Hey Google.
Send a text message to Francis Ko.
What's the message?
Hey, still up for lunch tomorrow?
I got, hey, still up for lunch tomorrow.
Ready to send it?
No.
Okay, what's the message?
Hey, are you still up for lunch tomorrow?
I got, hey, are you still up for lunch tomorrow?
Ready to send it?
Sending your message to Francis Co.
Here's how you could ask it to use a specific app, in this case Google Maps, to help you locate businesses of interest, to get driving directions, or to directly start navigating to a particular location.
Hey Google.
Use Google Maps to locate Hollywood film studios near me.
Okay, opening Google Maps.
Hey Google, get me driving directions to Disney Studios.
Hey Google, use Google Maps to get me driving directions to Disney Studios.
Hey Google, navigate to Disney Studios.
So I'll just note here that if I did not specify Google Maps in my instruction, then
I would get slightly different results.
So you can try this out by asking the assistant to use a specific app that's installed on
your phone to perform your desired task.
For example, play music or set a reminder.
Coming up next, some models allow you to input prompts that are not just text, but also images
and text.
These are called multimodal models.
Let's see how you can prompt with both images and text.
Next.