You may have at some point tried to scroll through a discussion forum post and all its replies and
tried to make sense of it. Or maybe you had a similar situation with your own social media
post and all of its replies. Let's see how you can synthesize all the replies by labeling them.
When you have many many distinct pieces of text, perhaps written by different people,
and want to make sense of all of it, it may help to label them by topic. For example,
with keywords such as love, positive, excited, negative, sad, and so on. Then you can group them
based on those labels, and based on the text that is grouped together, you can summarize key points
for each group. To look at how to synthesize information from many people, let's use, for
example, a public discussion forum, Reddit. And I'll just make a quick reminder of privacy that
If you have some internal discussion forum, you probably don't want to use a publicly hosted model.
Probably try something with a downloaded model.
So in Reddit, I'll search for discussions about the Olympics and breaking.
This particular original poster is asking why breaking will not be included in the 2028 Olympic Games,
whereas dressage has been included for many, many years.
And if you scroll down, you can see that there are many, many replies.
Some may disagree, some may agree, and some may be talking about something else.
So how can you enlist the help of a chatbot to help you label and synthesize this information?
Let's start out by getting the web link to this discussion forum post
and first test it out with a simple task to help us verify if it's doing what we hope it will do.
If you recall earlier in the course, you learned about testing a chatbot
or actually any AI-enabled software before you rely on it.
Let's use Notebook LM.
You can see that you can upload documents, connect to Google Docs, paste in text, or provide
a web link.
So let's use the web link option.
I'll go back to the website, get the link to that discussion forum post, and paste it
here.
Now you can see on the left-hand column, it displays that source article, and you can
expand it to verify that it indeed is the text from that discussion forum post.
So let's ask it for a simple task.
ask it to count the number of replies that it can see that are in this discussion forum post.
And you can see that it's trying to be cautious, and it says that the source material does not
explicitly say how many people there are. So you can try to ask a few follow-up questions and let
it know that you're not expecting it to give a precise answer, also acknowledging some of the
concerns that it might raise about not having enough information to answer the question. So these are
the two follow-up questions that I'm going to ask. So I'll try again and ask it to count the number
of replies that it can find even if some of the replies are not visible. It still responds very
cautiously that because it can't see all the replies which might be hidden by other links,
it's not willing to give an exact number. So I'll ask another follow-up question asking it to count
the number of replies even if it's a rough estimate. And now at least it gives me a number,
In this case, 214.
To better understand why it was so cautious, you can go back to the source and scroll to
the bottom, and you can see that the bottom says there are more replies, but these are
not visible on the webpage.
You can take a closer look at the original website, and if you scroll all the way down,
you can see that there's a red button that you can click on that says view more comments.
Only after you click on that does it load additional comments.
So to get all the replies, you just keep scrolling down and clicking on view more comments until
it shows all the replies. And in case the chatbot is not able to use a web link to see all the text
in that discussion forum post, let's go ahead and copy the text and open up a word processor
to paste that text in. Notice that for this particular site, if I do a regular paste,
it actually won't show anything. So let me go ahead and undo that and then just paste in
the pure unformatted text. Okay, it looks like there's 673 pages worth of text. And if I scroll
back to the top, I can verify that this is the text from that discussion forum post. And you can do the
same check and ask it to perform the simple task of counting the number of replies in the discussion
forum post. But now we're using the document instead of the link to the website. So I'll go
ahead and connect to Google Docs and find that file. While it's loading, I'll also uncheck the
previous source, which was from the web link, because now I want to have my prompts make use
of the uploaded Google Doc instead.
And you can open up the source again on the left
just to verify that it has the content
that you're expecting.
Now let's go ahead and give it the same task
to count the number of replies.
And it says it counts 289 replies
and also provides some detail
on why counting the replies can be tricky.
So the main takeaway I hope you get from this
is that it really helps to verify
that the data you're providing
is what you expect it to be.
In the case of providing a web link,
that may not provide all the content
in the discussion forum post
because some of it is hidden unless you click on a button to load more comments.
Now you're ready to synthesize this information,
and going forward, I'm going to be using that uploaded document instead of the web link.
Something you might be curious about is,
what are all the sports that people are talking about when they reply,
and how many users are talking about each category of sport?
Let's go ahead and see what this says.
It takes a bit of time, maybe about a minute, so I'm speeding up the video here.
you can see that breaking and dressage are mentioned 20 to 30 times, and it also mentions
other sports such as surfing. One thing I'd like to point out is in the prompt I specified that the
count should be one count per reply, because in this case I don't want to have multiple sentences
about breaking or multiple sentences about dressage from the same user to be counted multiple times.
And you will notice if you write this prompt without specifying one count per reply that
that you'll get a higher count number.
The really cool thing here is if you scroll through
this long list, there are many sports that
at least I wouldn't have thought of looking for,
including poodle haircutting,
although even the chatbot is able to suggest
that poodle haircutting probably was meant as a joke.
If you were trying to perform this task
in a time before large language models became so helpful,
you would have to write some traditional code
that would look for keywords and would list out
specific sport names to look for and then count.
But now you can just ask a chatbot, look for sports.
And now with chatbots, you can actually apply labels that are probably too difficult to create
just by searching for keywords.
For instance, you may be interested in whether each reply agrees with the view of the original
poster or disagrees with the original poster, or perhaps is talking about something else.
So the next prompt you can try is label each reply as to whether it agrees, disagrees,
or other, and then output that in a table where the column headers include the username,
the original quote from that reply, as well as the label.
Let's try this out.
This takes some time, maybe about a minute, so I'm speeding up the video here.
And it looks like it's output a table.
The chatbot tries to clarify that it's only outputting information for replies where it
was able to give a proper label.
Here's an example where the reply disagrees with the original poster.
Here's an example where the reply agrees with the original poster.
And here is an example where the reply is talking about something else.
And this particular tool, as well as many other chatbots, allow you to copy that table
if you want to put it into a spreadsheet, for instance.
And it looks like you can also click on Save so that it saves it within this application
if you want to refer to it later.
So that table was actually an intermediate step towards the end goal, which is really
to synthesize what all these replies are saying.
So the next step is to build upon that table and count how many replies agree and how many
disagree and also to summarize the key arguments made for each of these labels.
So let's try this out.
For those that agree with the original poster, it mentions lack of excitement for spectators
as well as some explanations with citations.
Other main themes include accessibility and elitism.
Another one is animal welfare concerns.
For those that disagree with the original poster, some of the themes include the physical and
technical demands of dressage, teamwork and partnership, and the historical significance
and tradition of that sport.
So the app that you've seen so far has been customized to really help you work with documents.
In case you're using a regular chatbot, you would take the extra step of pasting in the
text of that source material as part of the prompt.
Something that I think is worth trying is to put your task at the start of the prompt
and also put that same task at the end of the prompt, so the document is in the middle.
So why is that?
Some AI researchers have noticed that large language models tend to do better at a task
when the relevant information is at the beginning or the end of the prompt, as opposed to in the middle.
You can compare this to how the human mind remembers a list of words.
For example, if I give you a long list of words and I read it aloud to you,
then ask you to remember all the words that I said,
For example, I might start with pineapple, then camera, and then list many, many words.
Somewhere in the middle, I'll mention a puppy, and then I'll mention more words.
And then finally, I'll wrap up with rainbow and pizza.
In the field of psychology, researchers have found that the human brain
might have a better chance of recalling some of the words that were at the start of the list.
For example, pineapple.
This is called the primacy effect.
And they've also noticed that the human brain is more likely to remember the last few words in that list.
For example, pizza. This is called the recency effect. AI researchers have noticed a similar
effect with large language models. And what some AI researchers have found with large language
models is that if some information is contained in the middle of a large piece of text, then that
might get lost. For example, you may have forgotten that there was a puppy in the middle of all that.
And they've been calling this Lost in the Middle, which is actually the name of the research paper,
Lost in the Middle, How Large Language Models Use Long Contexts. The researchers note a slight
improvement when a prompt has the task provided at the beginning and also at the end of the prompt.
But they also have a caveat that for more complicated tasks like answering questions
over many, many documents, this doesn't seem to make a big difference. But you can try it out to
see if it makes a difference when you use it. So just put in the task at the top, paste in the text,
and then put in the task again at the bottom.
Otherwise, if you just want to write the task once,
then place the task at the beginning,
followed by the text of the source material.
The reason this can help a bit is that much of the data
that these large language models are trained on
tends to be provided where the instruction is at the very beginning
and the other contextual information, like a document, is placed after that.
And if this is too much information,
then you can forget everything I just said
and just remember to surround your source material with delimiters.
Coming up next, you can also use a chatbot to translate from one language to another,
and you'll have much more control over how it performs that translation.
Let's look at how to transform text from one language to another using a chatbot next.