One of the ways you could use chatbots for evaluation is by doing qualitative scoring
on things like essays. Let's take a look at how you can prompt a chatbot to help you with that.
You can have a chatbot play the role of a teacher by helping you check your work
and help you think things through if you need some feedback. So given a problem you're trying
to solve, you first try out the solution yourself, then share it with a chatbot teacher. The chatbot
chatbot can first work out its own solution, compare it to the student's solution, and
if needed, give feedback and hints for how to reach the correct answer.
I'm calling this task "Grading" because you and the chatbot are working on a problem where
there is one "correct" answer.
Here's the problem we're trying to solve.
You may recognize it from earlier in the course.
And for this example, let's have Meta AI play the role of the student.
So here's the student's solution.
And here is the grading task.
First ask the chatbot to work out the problem on its own.
Then compare its solution to the student's solution.
Then decide if the student's solution is correct or not.
If the student's solution is incorrect, give them some hints.
Below that you can provide the original task or problem that the student is asked to solve,
and also the student's solution that's being graded.
And let's use HuggingChat, which also hosts the Meta Llama model.
So meta is grading meta.
That's so meta.
Here's the start of the prompt.
And let's copy in the logic problem.
Then let's get the student solution and copy that in.
And let's see what happens.
Looks like the teacher chatbot incorrectly thinks that the answer is yes.
And so it says that the student is correct and does not need any hints.
So I tried this a couple times before filming, and sometimes the LLAML model as the grader
correctly figures out the answer is no and gives the student hints to get the correct
But sometimes the grader also gets it wrong, so I think it's helpful to keep in mind that
the grader might also get the answer wrong as well.
Let's try this again, but this time I'll choose another open source model also hosted
on Hugging Chat called QN, which is produced by Alibaba.
So QN will now play the role of the teacher, and I'll repeat the same prompt.
So in this case, looks like the teacher model works through the solution and correctly states
that the answer is no.
It then reviews the student's reasoning and compares it to the teacher's reasoning.
It also explains why the student's reasoning led to the incorrect answer.
Finally, the teacher provides some hints to help the student figure out the correct solution.
So that's pretty nice.
Maybe you can try this out sometime when you would like some feedback.
And for this example, maybe you can give the teacher's feedback back to the student chatbot
and see if that helps it get the right answer.
Next, let's look at evaluating someone's work when it's a more open-ended task, like an essay.
We'll look at qualitative scoring next.