One particular tool you'll come across when you work with chatbots is an image generation tool.
Let's see how you can use tools to help you generate images.
Image generation is done by more than one category of models, but most recently,
the category of models that have been performing really well are called diffusion models.
The way diffusion models work is they start with an image that's just a bunch of random pixels,
which we call noise.
A diffusion model slowly removes some of that noise a bit at a time,
as if it expects that there is an image underneath all that noise.
And it does this in a repeated iterative process.
Each time, it looks at the image as if there is a coherent picture or painting
behind all that random noise, and it tries to remove that noise.
When it's removed enough of the noise, then you get an image.
And something I'll point out here is that in those earlier iterations,
it's not that the model already knows what the final image looks like behind all that noise.
So those green lines that you see in the earlier iterations could have turned into a frog,
but could have also turned into a turtle or a tree.
To guide a diffusion model to create a specific image,
the models are trained to take in both an image and text label that describes that image.
So when you use a diffusion model, you'll include a prompt that describes the image that you're hoping for,
such as frog with a balloon.
The diffusion model attempts to create an image that matches this text.
Some people have described this process as similar to when a sculptor starts with a rock and carves out a statue.
One of my friends actually said it reminded him of this quote.
I saw the angel in the marble and carved until I set him free.
This quote is by the artist Michelangelo.
There are several sites that let you try out image generation.
I'll demonstrate this with Meta AI.
You can click on this pen icon on the left, which takes you to the page that generates images.
So I'll ask it to generate an image of a pineapple cake.
So these are pretty nice images of pineapple cakes.
But I was actually thinking about a particular kind of pineapple cake.
So let me be more specific.
Generate an image of a Taiwanese pineapple cake.
So that's actually closer to what I was thinking about,
because Taiwanese pineapple cakes are rectangular and have that kind of flaky texture on the outside.
Similar to when you prompt a large language model,
when you prompt a diffusion model, you can give more detail in your prompt to describe the image that you want.
I can say a frog holding a red balloon.
Then if I add in the style of a Banksy,
it changes this to a slightly more cartoonish looking image of a frog holding a red balloon.
These image generation models are also provided as tools that a large language model has access to.
For instance, if you go to chatGPT and ask it to generate an image,
the chatbot will actually call an image generation model, in this case, Dolly3 by OpenAI.
So I can ask within chatGPT, generate an image of a purple emoji ball.
So that's pretty good. I had something slightly different in mind.
I'll ask it to generate four images of a purple emoji ball where the emoji ball is a stress ball.
So it looks like it's output images that have a softer texture as if it's a squishy rubber ball.
Sometimes you may encounter a copyright restriction if you ask a model to generate an image in the style of a famous artist.
For example, I can ask in chat GPT to generate an image of a frog holding a red balloon, and that's fine.
Now, if I ask it to generate a frog holding a red balloon in the style of a Banksy, here's what it says.
It wasn't able to generate the image due to content policy restrictions.
And it's helpful to keep in mind that even when there aren't restrictions placed on the particular software that you're using,
it's probably best to avoid generating images that you think might be harmful to other people.
Oftentimes, we as society rely on photographs to reflect reality.
So it's important to be careful about generating images that look like realistic photographs,
especially images of people.
Coming up next, you'll practice using personal assistants to help you use apps on your phone.
Hey Siri!
Hey Google!
Alexa!