So you've just been invited to be a judge on a TV show called "Debating with the Stars."
For each round, all participants are given the same debate topic and asked to give their opening statement.
Your task as a judge is to review their statements and give them each a score.
Let's see how a chatbot can help you decide how to judge these debates.
We're going to simulate the debate participants with several open models that are hosted on Hugging Chat.
These include Meta Llama, QN, Command R+, Microsoft Fee, and Mistral Nemo.
Here's the debate topic.
Pineapples are better than anchovies as pizza toppings.
And since we're going to prompt chatbots to perform a task, here is the prompt for these debate participants.
Given the following debate topic, write an opening statement that agrees with the statement.
And we'll have some hosted proprietary models play the role of judges.
Here, we'll use Gemini, Claude, and ChatGPT.
And here is the task for the judges.
The following debate participants have been given a debate topic, and each participant has provided their argument.
Here are the judging instructions.
And it asks the judge to list out criteria for judging, to then evaluate each participant's argument,
and after reviewing the arguments, provide a ranking of the participants, as well as explain your reasoning.
And here's the first debate participant, Meadow Llama.
And don't worry about reading through all these opening statements.
I think it will be a fun exercise after this video for you to try this out yourself
and spend some time studying how various chatbots
attempt to make persuasive arguments.
Now let's see what Qwen says about the debate topic.
Next is Coheres, Command + R+.
And here is Microsoft V.
Finally, we have Mr. Nemo making the case for pineapples over anchovies.
The first judge is Gemini.
I'll start by giving it the task for being a judge.
Then I will give it the names of the debate participants as well as each participant's
opening statement.
And it lists out some criteria for judging, including argument strength, evidence, relevance
to the topic, creativity, and overall appeal.
And for each participant and for each criteria, it lists out what it thought about that opening
statement, as well as providing a score for each participant.
So for Lama, it gave a score of 9.
For QN, it gave a score of 8.
For Cohere, score of 8.
Microsoft Fee, also 8.
And Mr. Nemo, a score of 9.
And I would like to point out that you don't have to take these scores as the final score
you would actually give to the debate participants.
but it's actually quite helpful to get some ideas for what criteria you would use for evaluating
these open-ended essays. And it's also very helpful to see how other chatbots would perform
the same evaluation. So now let's have Claude by Anthropic also play the role of the judge.
As before, let's give it the task for being a judge and also give it the arguments from each
debate participant. And the output's really fast, so don't worry, I'm going to scroll back up to
walk through this. So for criteria, it lists the structure, persuasiveness, evidence, also addressing
counter arguments, creativity, the delivery, and also relevance. Now for each participant and each
criteria, it also provides a score up to 10, and it adds them up for a total score. So with meta,
it gave it a score of 59. For QN, it gave a score of 54. Command R+, it gave a score of 54.
Microsoft Fee gave a score of 59.
Mr. Nemo, score of 59.
And now it provides an overall ranking
and also gives an explanation for the ranking.
Now let's have ChatGPT play the role of judge.
So we'll give it the same task
and the same arguments from the same debate participants.
And you can see similar criteria
from the previous two judges.
There's clarity, persuasiveness, relevance,
creativity, providing evidence, and engagement.
And for each participant and each criteria, it also gives a score and then adds them up.
So for Meta, it gave a score of 52.
For QN, it gave a score of 48.
For Command R+, it got a score of 48.
For Microsoft Fee, it got a score of 55.
And for Mr. Nemo, it got a score of 49.
And now it provides a ranking as well as overall feedback, as well as an explanation of its rankings.
So you might notice that different judges give different numeric scores and even different
rankings for the same debate participants, just like in real life.
So how can you generalize this process to help you with your tasks?
In addition to evaluating people's essays or their debate arguments, you can make use
of chatbots to help you evaluate other chatbots.
Since many tasks that you give a chatbot are asking them to also give an open-ended answer
where there's no one single right answer, you're going to need some way to measure
how well they do on the task.
And it's still important for you as a human to make the final call on which chatbot or group of chatbots you wish to use for a particular task,
but it can really speed things up to help you get ideas for objective evaluation criteria and help you think through how you want to define quality.
So for any task that you ask a chatbot to perform, you can send its output to another chatbot for evaluation.
Then you can take the original output and the evaluation of it to help you decide how well the chatbot performed at that task.
In the AI research community, they've been calling this model-graded evaluation.
Coming up next, you'll practice chatting with a chatbot, starting with talking about whatever's on your mind.