When you have a conversation with a chatbot, you can actually prompt it to take the initiative and lead the conversation.
For example, you could have it be an interviewer and help you do interview prep.
Recently, you wrote a letter to the president of Furry Friends Forever Cat Cafe,
asking them to consider you for a position at that cafe.
And congratulations, they're giving you an interview.
and the interviewer will probably ask you some questions, listen to your answers, and ask more
follow-up questions. Interviews can be a little bit intimidating, but it gets easier with practice.
And practicing with your friends is great, but you could also practice with a chatbot. Let's see how
you can do that. You can start by defining the chatbot's role as an interviewer for a job
position. The position that you're applying for is cat cafe manager. So here's the job description.
provide attention to cats, feed the cats, make coffee for guests, give cat petting guidelines
to guests, and clean the cats and litter boxes. And here's the task for the interviewer. The
interviewer will ask any three questions that they find relevant to this position, one at a time.
So by explicitly saying three questions, you're helping it to set limits to how long the interview
will last. And by asking it to ask one question at a time, you're telling the chatbot to make this
feel like a live in-person interview instead of having the chatbot list out the entire list of
interview questions all at once, which some chatbots I noticed will do unless you explicitly tell them
to ask questions one at a time. Here are more details on the process that you're going to ask
the chatbot to follow as an interviewer. And part of the reason I suggest being very detailed here
is because by default, a chatbot tends to output all the interview questions all at once, and
sometimes even starts to answer its own questions as if it is both the interviewer and interviewee.
So here's the process for this interview. So here you'll ask it to repeat this pattern
for the interview. Ask a prepared question. Wait for the interviewee to answer the question.
Then ask a follow-up question based on the interviewee's reply. These follow-up questions
are really helpful because they really simulate what happens in a real interview, where the
direction that the interview takes is in part determined by your responses and the interviewer's
reaction to those responses. It also lets you practice moving the interview in a certain
direction because if you want to talk about something that really helps you stand out,
even if the question isn't directly asking about it, you can find some way to bring it up so that
then the interviewer, whether it's a chatbot or a real person, will then shift the conversation
towards that interesting topic that you just brought up. Okay, so let's continue on with the
instructions. Wait to allow the interviewee to respond to your follow-up question. And I'm putting
this here because sometimes the chatbot will ask a follow-up question and then immediately ask its
next prepared question. So this is reminding the chatbot to pause and really make this a two-way
back-and-forth conversation. The next step is after the interviewee responds to the follow-up question,
move on to the next prepared question. And remember earlier in the prompt, you've asked the interviewer
to ask three prepared interview questions. Finally, after you have asked your prepared question and
your follow-up questions, conclude the interview. And this is important because we don't want the
interview to go on indefinitely because the next step is asking the interviewer to provide feedback
on your interview performance. The last part of the prompt is to request feedback from the
interviewer. For each of the prepared questions, rate the response on a scale of 1 to 5, where 5 is
highest score. Provide some suggestions for how the interviewee can improve their interview answers.
So as you may recall from earlier in the course, chatbots can help you with qualitative scoring
of open-ended responses or essays. And so they can also give a qualitative score to your interview
responses. Now you don't have to treat these numeric scores as an absolute fact, and even for
these suggestions for how to improve, you can reflect on whether these apply to your situation.
But one thing that I think can be helpful is to practice receiving constructive criticism
graciously, because demonstrating that you can take feedback and work on improving based
on that feedback is something that interviewers will find very valuable.
So for privacy, both for myself and for any existing company that I worked for or worked
for in the past, I will practice the mock interview with a model that I can download
using LM Studio.
I'll demonstrate with Gemma, which is the open source sibling of Gemini by Google.
I think it does pretty well in asking one question at a time, asking follow-up questions that are related to my actual responses,
and it seems to do a good job of maintaining the role of an interviewer.
So I'll give it the instructions for playing the role of an interviewer, as well as the process I want it to follow for conducting the interview.
So it does a good job of immediately jumping into the role right away, welcoming me to the interview, and asking the first question about cat body language.
And I'm trying my best to respond and also mention when a cat's body language may indicate anxiety.
The interviewer shows that they're actively listening because they pick on what I talked about in terms of tension and anxiety of a cat.
It then moves on and asks me for a specific scenario where a client at a cat cafe may have misunderstood the cat's body language.
I try to respond that it would explain to the customer that both for the safety of the customer and the comfort of the cat,
to usually take a hands-off approach and let the cats approach the humans first.
And so the interviewer responds good example and ties this into their original question
about how body language might be misinterpreted.
Next, the interviewer asks me how I would handle a litter of new kittens that arrive at the cat cafe.
And I respond that adult cats and baby cats might behave differently
and recommend placing the kittens in a separate room where trained staff members can interact with the kittens
but leave a viewing window open to allow guests to watch the kittens from a safe distance.
And it looks like the interviewer picks up on my suggestion
and also seems to recommend giving the kittens a safe space.
And now the interviewer wraps up the interview
and now is giving me feedback on each of my responses to his questions.
The feedback it gives is a bit general,
mostly saying I could do more research on the topic it's asking about.
The cool thing is I've tried this out before filming
and I gave some really bad interview answers.
For example, I said that I'm really allergic to cats.
And some of the chatbots do a good job of pointing out that this is an issue and that maybe being a manager of a cat cafe may not be the best employment option for me.
So when you have a chance, please try this out for yourself.
Download a model onto your computer for privacy and prompt it to be an interviewer for a job that you're interested in.
Now, because I've tried this out with a couple chatbots, I will just tell you up front that this won't work all the time.
And depending on the large language model you're using, you may need to write different instructions
to get them to behave in the way that makes it feel like a natural interview.
But I found that even when a large language model isn't quite doing what I'm expecting it to do,
that's actually good practice for me to rewrite my prompts in a way to steer it in the direction
and the behavior that I'm looking for. Coming up next, you can actually have a chatbot chat with
another chatbot and collaborate to perform a task. And this could potentially give you better results
than if you were to work with just one chatbot.
Let's check out chatbot to chatbot collaboration next.