Sometimes you need to come up with creative ideas.
Like for example...
Hang on a second.
Let me ask a chatbot for help.
In the meantime, let's take a look at how you can use chatbots to come up with creative ideas.
Sometimes when you're trying to be creative,
you can ask a chatbot to give you options to help you think of new ideas.
For example, you can say, "Tell me a joke about puppies."
So here it gave me one joke.
Why did the puppy sit in the shade?
Because it didn't want to be a hot dog.
But it would help to ask for more than one option.
So you can say instead, suggest several options for a joke about puppies.
So now you have a couple options.
Feel free to rewind a bit to read through all of them
or prompt a chatbot yourself to see what you get. If you find a joke you like and want variations
in a similar style, you can ask it to analyze the joke, explain why it's funny, and then suggest
some similar jokes. Why don't dogs make good dancers? Because they have two left feet. So I
can say explain the structure and what method it uses to make the punchline be funny or interesting
and then suggests some jokes that use a similar method for the punchline.
And here, it identifies that two left feet is an idiom in English,
which describes when someone maybe isn't so coordinated and therefore not very good at dancing.
And then it tries to suggest some jokes that have the same type of wordplay that you saw in the first joke.
So for example, this joke, why did the scarecrow win an award?
because he was outstanding in his field.
And it explains the joke, because outstanding in a field
is a play on the literal idea of a scarecrow standing in a field.
So I encourage you to try this out for yourself.
Either pause the video now or wait till the end of the video,
and you can analyze some jokes and see if you can prompt a chatbot
to suggest some jokes that have a similar style or setup.
Here's an example to get you started.
Here's this joke about eating salads and cakes that you may recall from earlier.
And I'm actually a bit curious if you find this funny or not,
because I've tried this on a couple people and got mixed results.
But at least it makes me laugh when I tell it to myself.
There's also this funny phrase that I came up with.
I wish I remembered what I was thinking when I was inside the box.
Or this one, which I read somewhere online.
I wish I paid more attention in my first rodeo.
And don't worry if you don't get why this is supposed to be funny, maybe you can ask a chatbot to explain.
And maybe after you try asking a chatbot to tell some jokes or explain some jokes,
you can decide for yourself whether you think AI has a sense of humor or not.
You may recall that chatbots sometimes hallucinate,
especially when you ask it about yourself if it doesn't have information about you.
You can treat this behavior as a feature instead of a bug if you ask it to daydream about your future life journey.
For example, you may be planning your next steps in your career, maybe you're starting
out in your career, and it helps to read other people's biographies to get a sense of what
kind of life you want to live.
And it might also be fun to read an inspiring story about your future self.
And you can customize this story based on your personal interests and hobbies.
I'll start out by giving the chatbot a role as a fortune teller who tells inspiring stories
of a person's future life.
And I'll give the fortune teller some background info.
the person's name, Francis, Ko, their interests, hobbies, and values.
I specify the pronoun because it sometimes tends to default to he and him unless you specify this.
So let's see what the future may hold for Francis.
If you want, you can try this on yourself with your own hobbies and your own personal interests and passions
to see what the chatbots tell you might be in your future.
And I hope it might give you some inspiration for what you want to do next.
Let's go on to the next video to learn about one of these synthesized tasks, which is to summarize text.