You can use chatbots to transform text from one form to another. For example, you can also use
chatbots to translate from one language to another. If you took the machine translation part of this
course, you used it to translate an idiom or saying, and depending on the context, the translation tool
may have translated this into an idiom in the target language, or it may have translated this
literally. You can also use chatbots to perform translation as well. And the nice thing is that
you can ask it to translate to more than one target language at the same time. Let's see how a chatbot
translates the phrase "every cloud has a silver lining" into multiple languages. And here I'll use
Copilot. So it translates to Spanish, French, German, Chinese, Japanese, Russian, Arabic, Portuguese,
Hindi. And I've actually tried this out with multiple chatbots. Most of them do pretty well
with translating to Spanish. Here I'll look at the Chinese translation, and in this case it's
suggesting a phrase that looks a little bit more literal and is not the equivalent idiom in Chinese
that I'm looking for. But even if you're not familiar with the target language that you're
trying to translate to, you can ask a chatbot to help you out and check if it's providing a
translation that a native speaker would recognize. So you can ask a follow-up question: for the
For the Chinese translation, is this a common idiom or expression in Chinese?
If not, can you suggest common idioms or expressions that have the same meaning?
Let's see what it says.
So now that it has a chance to double-check itself, the chatbot says that this is not
a common expression, and lists three expressions that might be more recognizable to people who
speak that language.
And the first expression that it suggested, 塞翁师马, 言之非福, means "a
a blessing in disguise. And that was actually the idiom that I was thinking about as the equivalent
to every cloud has a silver lining. And again, if you're not familiar with the target language,
you can ask the chatbot to explain what that idiom means. So for the next follow-up question,
you can ask, for the first idiom referring to the list that it just output, please give some
background on the meaning and origin of this idiom. And let's see what it says. And so it explains
that bad luck can turn into good luck and also the other way around. Good luck might turn into bad
luck. And it tells the story that is the origin of this phrase. It's about a man who loses his horse
and his neighbors say, oh, that's too bad. And he says, well, maybe it's not so bad. Then that same
horse that ran away came home and also came back with an additional horse, who I'm sure is just a
friend. So the neighbors say, oh, that's great. But then the owner says, well, maybe it's not that
great. Later, the owner's child is riding that new horse, the one who's just a friend, and accidentally
falls off and breaks his leg. So the neighbors all say, oh, that's too bad. But the father says,
well, maybe it's not so bad. Then one day there's a war, so all the young people have to go off and
fight in that war, and many of them get hurt or worse. But because the man's son had a broken leg,
The son was not able to go to war, and therefore he was able to stay home and stay safe.
So that's kind of a cool background story to the idiom.
And there's a lot of idioms in other languages that have similar meanings, as every cloud has a silver lining.
So I encourage you to ask a chatbot to identify idioms in other languages that have the same meaning,
and to explore the origins of those idioms.
And the nice thing about performing translation with a chatbot is you're no longer just limited to
surrounding a phrase with certain keywords or phrases to encourage the translation service
to provide the idiomatic translation or alternatively the literal translation.
Now with a chatbot, you can directly ask it for the idiomatic translation
and even ask it to propose a couple different options because there may be more than one.
Let's now try to translate another idiom.
It's a piece of cake into French and ask for different options for expressions
that might have the same meaning.
And let's ask it to label each of these options as to whether it's a figurative or literal word-for-word translation.
So I'll go ahead and use Mistral, because they're based in France, and have an emphasis on the French language.
It first provides the literal translation, which is literally a piece or slice of cake,
and then it provides a couple figurative translations, including a game for children, as easy as saying hello,
and this is kind of funny, with a finger up the nose.
So which one might be more commonly understood?
Well, you can ask the chatbot that exact question.
For these options, which are more commonly used in everyday language and conversation?
So here's what it says.
A game of children is listed first as the most common expression.
You can think of it as child's play.
Followed by as easy as saying hello.
And followed by with a finger up the nose.
And as before, I do encourage you to try this out with a couple different chatbots
because they may give different results.
and it will help you to review a couple different chatbots outputs to help you decide which
translation to use. In addition to foreign languages, it might help to know that you can
translate into Morse code, which is an alphabet that you can signal using a mirror and some sunlight,
or even a flashlight. You might have seen this demonstrated in a spy movie, for instance.
So here's a scenario where this might come in handy. Say you're sitting on a beautiful tropical
island eating some fresh pineapples. In the distance, you see a ship in the ocean, and you
decide you want to send them a signal in Morse code with a mirror and the sunlight. Thankfully,
you took this free online course that suggested the benefits of downloading compressed language
models onto your personal computer, and you also have that same computer with you. So you turn on
the computer, and here's what you ask the chatbot to do. Convert the following text to Morse code
and break it down letter by letter. SOS, I'm stuck on a deserted island. And it's still good to
double check if this looks right to you. For instance, it looks like the letter S is consistent
here and here. And here's the letter O. It looks like S is a dot, two dashes, followed by a dot,
and O is three dashes. But let's double check this. So we can rewrite this prompt by adding this
to the beginning. List out the alphabet in Morse code. Then convert this to Morse code and break
down letter by letter. And here's the same message as before. Let's try this out. So here is the
updated prompt, and you can see that it's first listing out the alphabet in Morse code. And now
it's converting the message to Morse code. Let's scroll back up and check the alphabet for S and O.
So S is actually three dots, not what we saw earlier. O is three dashes, which is the same
as what we saw earlier. And now you can see that the message SOS looks like this. S is three dots,
Here and here, O is three dashes.
You can also do an internet search, and here in Wikipedia,
you can verify that S is three dots and O is three dashes.
So maybe you can practice how you might prompt a chatbot to
convert your message into Morse code, and your future self will thank you
when you encounter a situation where it's really useful.
Next up, you can transform text using chatbots in other ways as well.
Let's look at how you might reword and rewrite text.
Let's go on to the next video.