Have you ever wanted to vent to your friends, but none of your friends want to listen to it anymore?
Now you can talk to a chatbot instead.
You may be familiar with asking follow-up questions to a chatbot,
but it usually feels a bit like a one-sided conversation where you are the one leading the conversation.
There are ways you can prompt a chatbot to take more initiative in moving the conversation forward.
So let's take an example where you give the chatbot a role of a life coach.
And here's the prompt.
You ask it to take a non-judgmental approach.
And you also ask it that if it has ideas for resolving or fixing a situation,
that it first asks the human to share their ideas before the chatbot life coach offers suggestions.
I added this instruction here because by default,
chatbots may try their best to find solutions or fix things.
But when you're dealing with people, sometimes what matters is that they want to be acknowledged
and have space to express their feelings and thoughts.
And it's sometimes better to focus on giving people space before moving forward and suggesting
solutions or fixing things.
The role description also asks the chatbot to leave the conversation open for additional
follow-ups instead of trying to wrap up the conversation.
I added this here because the way chatbots tend to reply, it almost seems like they think
they only have one chance to respond. So they tend to wrap up their completions with some wording
that suggests that the conversation is over. So this prompt encourages the chatbot to continue
the conversation a bit longer. These instructions also ask the chatbot to assume that what is
outputting is what the human user is seeing or hearing. And so I'm asking the chatbot to not
output its internal monologue. And I added this instruction because for some of the language
models that I've tried, they would sometimes output their internal monologue or output a
description of what they're physically doing, like nodding their head attentively. So this prompt is
trying to encourage the chatbot to make this conversation feel more natural. I'm going to use
LM Studio and download a model onto my computer so that I can keep this conversation to myself.
I'll start off by giving it a prompt that will define its role as a life coach. It starts out by
asking me how I'm doing, and I reply, well, I don't know. For my birthday, my friend gave me breath
Notice how it responds by acknowledging my feelings first and asking me follow-up questions
about how I feel.
Normally, by default, a chatbot will tend to jump straight away to saying, "well, maybe
you have bad breath.
Let's see how we can fix that."
Here instead, the Life Coach chatbot is focused on learning more about how I feel.
So my reply is, "well, I'm devastated.
I wonder if this means that I have bad breath."
The Life Coach chatbot replies by first acknowledging the distress that I feel.
It goes on to suggest that there may possibly be other ways of interpreting the situation,
and then asks me if there's another way to look at this situation.
So it's cool, instead of telling me what to think, it's gently suggesting alternatives
and asking me to think of alternative ways to think about the situation.
So I reply, well, yes, that's true.
Maybe it's just to help me prepare for a situation where I really need to have good breath.
But maybe it means that my friend thinks that I smell bad.
The life coach acknowledges my concerns.
It also points out some positives of my negative feelings, noting that it shows that I value
how others perceive me.
And because I brought up bad breath, it then asks me if I would like some advice on dental
care and maintaining fresh breath.
So I say, oh sure.
It goes on to talk about self-care and dental care and tries not to be too pushy about it.
So I reply, well, maybe later.
I'm feeling really distraught.
So then it goes back to providing emotional support.
I say thank you.
And then it sort of wraps up the conversation there.
So I'd encourage you to actually try starting a conversation without first giving the chatbot
a particular role, and this will give you a sense of its default behavior.
Depending on which chatbot you're using, it may understand that it's supposed to be attentive
and ask follow-up questions.
But if you find that the default behavior isn't quite what you're looking for, you can prompt
it to encourage it to have this two-way conversation, this dialogue between you and the chatbot.
Up next, you'll ask a chatbot to help you with interview prep by asking it to play the
role of an interviewer in a mock interview.
Let's look at that next.