Chatbots can output text, but how can they interact with the world around them?
Let's take a look at how tools can allow chatbots to go beyond just outputting text.
If you think about your ability as a human to navigate the world around you, you rely
on your brain to think about what you want to do. But you also rely on the rest of your body,
like your arms and legs, to actually interact with the rest of the world and also discover
more about the world. So if you think about a large language model as a brain, you can give it
arms and legs so that it can interact with the rest of the software world, such as access the
internet or apps on your computer or phone. The software functions that a large language model
has the ability to run are called tools. When a tool is included, the flow of inputs and outputs
is a bit different than before. Let's look at how a large language model might call on a web search
tool. Suppose you ask in a prompt, who broke world records at the Paris Olympics? The model can choose
to just answer this without using the tool, but it may also decide that since this question is about
current events, it may need to do a web search. So the model outputs text that has a specific
standard format. For instance, within curly braces, it has the keyword tool in all capital letters,
followed by the name of the tool, web search. It also has the keyword query, followed by the query
I should go into the web search. This is still text that's output by the model, but since it's
formatted in a specific way, there is other software that can scan this completion, and when
it recognizes that this is a request to use a function, it redirects this output, meaning that
the user does not see this text. Instead, the chatbot runs the requested web search tool with
the given query. Then the search results, as well as the request to answer the user's original
question gets sent as a prompt to the model. The model can now answer the question with the
additional information and that answer is sent back to the user. Let's first see how a chatbot does
without having access to the web search tool. I'm going to use Hugging Chat because they allow you
to switch on and off access to tools. I'm using Microsoft Fee as the model with search web turned
off. The model answers the question about the Paris Olympics by sharing information about the
the Paris Olympics that were held in 1900. But if you might recall, Paris also held the Olympic Games
in 2024. Let's try this again with the same prompt, but with the web search tool turned on.
In Hugging Chat, you can click here to turn on the search web tool. Remember, this gives the model
the option to use the tool, but it can choose whether to use the tool or not. And here's the
same question. Who set world records at the Paris Olympic Games? This time, it cites its sources,
which are these websites at the bottom. And if I scroll back up, I can recognize that these
athletes competed in the recent Paris Olympics in 2024. Many tools tend to be traditional software
code. LLMs and traditional software both have different strengths that make it helpful for them
to work together for some tasks. Recall that LLMs are probabilistic, which means they output text
based on how likely each next word is to appear based on text that it learned from in its training.
As you saw earlier in the course, this means that if you give it the same input twice,
the outputs will not be identical. Traditional software code, in contrast, is deterministic,
which means that it follows a given set of instructions. So if you give it the same input
twice, you'll get the same exact output each time. Since LLMs are probabilistic, they're more
adaptable. By that I mean that they can respond to inputs that they haven't seen before and they
won't just output an error message. In contrast, traditional software is more brittle. If it
receives an input and doesn't have instructions on how to handle that input, it will either output
an error message or just not output anything at all. Let's say you want to tell a computer to
output the text, hello world. Having a computer print hello world is kind of a tradition for
anyone who is learning about computers or coding. And don't worry, I'm not asking you to learn about
coding in order to successfully complete this course. If I send this instruction, print hello
world, as it's written here, the computer will not understand and will output an error message.
I'll demonstrate this in Google Colab. Colab is kind of like Google Docs, but for coding. I'll
print hello world and I'll run the code by clicking on this play button. It doesn't understand,
so it outputs an error message and asks me, did you mean print with parentheses? So I'll create a
line of code and try again. I'll write print hello world and surround hello world with parentheses
and I'll run this. It gives me another error message and it asks perhaps you forgot a comma,
so I try again. I don't know where to stick the comma so I'll just stick it somewhere here
and I'll run it. It outputs yet another error message and again asks me if I forgot a comma.
So at this point I'm just reliving my first few years in college when I first tried to learn
computer programming. Fun times. In contrast to traditional code, large language models are more
adaptable. So I can write print hello world and first send it to an LLM. The LLM can figure out
that it probably should fix the code so that it can run, so it rewrites this code. Then the computer
runs that code and outputs hello world. So in Google Colab, I can click on this option, generate
with AI, it opens up a text box where I can send a prompt to their chatbot, which is probably Gemini.
I'll write print hello world, and it outputs this code. If I run this code, the computer outputs
hello world. LLens can do more than fix your code. They can also translate your ideas from human
readable language to computer code. So your prompt can also be python code to print hello world. The
model will think through what you're requesting, then output code, and then send that to the computer
to run. Let's try this out. You can click on generate with AI and then write Python code to
print hello world and it outputs code. I'll run it and it prints out hello world. So this is pretty
exciting but as before I always recommend having human review over whatever output you get from the
model. Here's an example to illustrate this. Let's say you want help with calculating the Fibonacci
sequence. So you don't need to know too much about the Fibonacci sequence but I'll just explain it in
case you're curious. The sequence looks like this. 0, 1, 1, 2, 3, 5, and so on. And this is how the
Fibonacci sequence is generated. You start with 0 and 1. Add them together to get the next number,
which is 1. Then you repeat this process. Take the most recent two numbers and add them together
to get the next number in the sequence. So 1 plus 1 is 2. 1 plus 2 is 3. 2 plus 3 is 5, and so on.
What if you want to get the 20th number, or any number in the sequence?
You can use computer code to calculate that, and you can ask an LLM to help you write that
code.
In Google Colab, you can click on Generate with AI, and here's the prompt: Write code
to calculate the 20th number in the Fibonacci sequence.
It outputs some code.
Don't worry about reading through this, that's not what I want you to focus on here.
I'll run this code, and it outputs 6765, which is in fact the 20th number in the Fibonacci
sequence. So it seems fine, but let me ask a follow-up question. Is the following code for
Fibonacci sequence efficient? And I'll copy the code from above to paste it in. Notice that it
doesn't let me paste in too much text, so I'm just going to copy the part of the code that describes
the algorithm. Now the chatbot outputs an explanation that the code is not efficient,
and it gives some explanations for why. Don't worry about trying to understand the details about why
it is inefficient. The point I would like you to focus on is that even if you get code that appears
to work, you may want to check if it's going to work for other inputs. For example, if it's
inefficient, it will take several minutes to run when you ask it for the 50th Fibonacci number.
In contrast, the efficient method would take a fraction of a second. So you may have a couple
questions. One is, why not just have the large language model directly calculate the Fibonacci
sequence instead of asking it to write code. Well, traditional code is more consistent, so when you
have code that is correct and efficient, you can reuse it and rely on it to follow the instructions
in the code. A nice thing about traditional code is that it's more computationally efficient. This
means it takes less time to run compared to running a several billion parameter large language model.
So it also uses less electricity, which also means fewer carbon emissions. So if you want to add a
couple numbers together, consider using a calculator instead of a large language model.
If you want to perform some repeatable math calculation, consider running some traditional
computer code, which you can ask an LLM to help you write. The other question you may have is,
why does the large language model output the inefficient version for calculating the
Fibonacci sequence? Well, for some background, many introductory computer science courses
start off with this exact Fibonacci sequence example. Teachers use this to illustrate the
importance of writing efficient code. And they do this by starting with the inefficient way of
writing this code. Then they show how slow it gets when you start asking for those larger Fibonacci
numbers. So the inefficient way of writing this code is all over the internet and in the text
that these large language models used to train on. Going back to the comparison of LLMs versus
traditional software code, LLMs can be unpredictable. If you give the same prompt to an LLM twice,
you'll get different outputs each time. Traditional software code is consistent. For the same inputs,
you get the same outputs. Let's look at an example of how a chatbot will give you different results
for the same prompt. Here's a task: use code to parse this document of a reddit post and its
replies to get the username and associated comment for the entire document. I'll put this as a table
with two columns: username and comment. Include the original poster and all the replies. I'll use
ChatGPT and upload this text file. The file contains text that I copied from this reddit
discussion that you may recall from earlier in the course about Olympics, breaking, and dressage.
So the chatbot writes some code and does some troubleshooting of its code, which is pretty cool.
Then it tries again, and now it outputs a table. But if you look at the output,
it doesn't look like it's got any comments in the column that says comment. I'm going to try this a
second time doing the same thing as before this time the output looks pretty good the column that
says comment appears to actually have the comment for each user so for the same input and task you
get different results each time and so if you get a chatbot to write some helpful code for you and
it works then i recommend you save it somewhere so that you can reuse it next let's take a look at
image generation you sometimes see image generation added as a tool that a chatbot can use it's
actually a different model independent of the large language model so let's learn a little bit more
about image generation