As you're reading or hearing about AI in the news or online, you may come across a lot of
vocabulary words. There's an expression "word salad" to refer to when there are just too many
vocabulary words that it's hard to understand some article or document. For example, there's
generative AI, often abbreviated as just Gen AI. There's transformers, GPT, GPUs, and these are
words that you might see in regular news articles about AI. Other words like quantized models,
distilled models, and pruned models might show up when you're reading about those compressed
downloadable models that you may have tried in this course. If you're reading a bit more about AI,
you might come across words such as foundation models, base models, and instruction tuned model.
You may also hear about retrieval augmented generation as well as agents. Each of these
are pretty big topics that probably deserve their own course, but even a brief conceptual
introduction to these topics might make it easier for you as you navigate your own learning
resources and start learning on your own. So let's take a brief look at what these words mean.
So what is generative AI? Well, it helps to also ask the question, what is non-generative AI? You
may have heard that generative AI is about creating something new. Let's look at some
examples of machine learning models and the tasks that they perform and see whether they're
generative or non-generative, and why. Let's start with an image classifier. It takes an image of a
dog, for instance, as input, and then outputs a piece of text that defines a class or category
from a predefined list of possible categories that the model has been trained to classify.
For instance, cute dog. Is this a generative task? No, and we'll discuss why in a little bit.
Let's look at an image generator. If you take a text description such as cute frog and input this
into an image generation model, it outputs an image of a cute frog. Is this generative? You may
have guessed from the description of the model that yes, this is a generative task. Let's look
at another example, a sentiment analysis model. For an input, you have a product review, such as,
I took this online course and it was fun. You send this to a sentiment analysis model, which outputs
one of a few possible classes such as positive, negative, or neutral. In this case, it outputs
positive. Is this generative? No, it's not. Now let's look at a text summarizer. You have a
transcript of an online course, and you send this to a model that summarizes text. It outputs a brief
summary that attempts to get at the essence of that transcript. So is this generative? Yes, it is.
If you look at the two examples where it is not generative, something they have in common is that
the kinds of outputs that these models can produce are limited. In this case, limited to a predefined
set of classes that the model is able to output. And they don't have to be classes either. They
could be numbers. For instance, if you have a model that tries to predict a person's life
expectancy based on their eating and sleeping habits, this is a non-generative model as well.
When you look at the two examples of models that are generative, in the first one, it produces a
new image that is not limited to some predefined set of images that it can produce. In the case of
the summarization model, it produces a new piece of text that is also considered free-form and
open-ended. In other words, the summarizer model can choose its own words as it attempts to perform
the task of summarizing a larger piece of text. And other generative models can also produce new
audio, such as music, or others can produce new tabular data, which are numbers and categories
that you would see in a spreadsheet. And by the way, you may hear different vocabulary words to
non-generative AI. The most common is discriminative AI. Another is predictive AI. You may also hear
it referred to as supervised learning or traditional AI. Just to keep this lecture simpler, I'll keep
referring to this as non-generative AI. But if you hear people mention any of the other terms,
especially if the overall discussion is about generative AI, then they're probably using these
words to refer to non-generative AI. An interesting aspect of what makes generative AI generative is
that the output from a generative task can be used as the input to another model. For instance,
you may recall with chatbot2chatbotcollaboration that you had one chatbot play the role of a writer
writing an opinion article for a newspaper. The article that it output was given as input to
another chatbot that played the role of the editor, which was tasked with reviewing and giving feedback
on that article. As another example, when an image generation model outputs an image, that image could
be sent as the input to another model, such as an image classifier model. So because the outputs of
generative models are usually rich in details and features, the outputs of generative AI models can
be used as features or inputs to other models, including for training other models.
Let's look at another comparison of generative and non-generative models in terms of what you
expect to be an acceptable output. For an image classifier, you give it an image and it outputs
a class. In this case, you would expect that there would be one correct answer. With similarity
search, which is also a non-generative model, you give it an image and it outputs a couple of images
that is selected from an existing set of images. So the expectation here is that the model selects
from an existing set of items. Now let's take a look at an image generation model. When you give
it some text that describes an image for it to create, there are many possible correct and new
outputs that the image generator could potentially create. So when it outputs a new image, our
expectation is that this is an image that was not retrieved from some database of images,
It's something new.
And if you were to give the image generator the same input text multiple times, you would
also expect it to generate other new images each time.
So our expectation of these models is that there are many possible correct and new answers,
probably infinitely many correct answers.
Another way to think of this is to compare non-generative AI to multiple-choice quizzes,
and to compare generative AI to an open-ended essay.
With a multiple choice quiz, there's a finite set of options for you to choose from.
With an open-ended essay, there are many ways that you could write that essay for it to
be considered a good essay.
And it's not limited to what the teacher might imagine to be possible essays that you
might write.
Is machine translation generative or not?
Well, if you had a model that was limited to single word translations, like a bilingual
dictionary, this would be non-generative.
It's similar to a classification task.
And you might not even need AI for this.
But how about when you're translating not a single word, but phrases and sentences,
like you saw in this course?
As you recall from the machine translation part of the course,
a translation model outputs open-ended text based on its interpretation of the input text.
For example, it would have to interpret whether to translate an expression,
like piece of cake, literally, or idiomatically.
So this is a generative task.
Well, how about question answering?
Well, before large language models got really good at this, there were other versions of
question-answering models that would do something simpler, where they would take two inputs,
both the question and also a document from which the model would search for the answer
to that question.
So this type of limited question-answering model would try to identify the relevant parts
of the source document that might answer the question.
This is non-generative because the model's output is limited to extracting direct quotes
from the source document.
In contrast, what you saw when you used large language models is that these models can answer questions in their own words,
and also they can use their own knowledge gained from training without having an additional source document.
So this is generative.
How about text summarization?
What you saw in this course is considered generative because the model is using its own interpretation and own wording to produce that summary.
How about text classification?
There are models that are designed to assign categories to text based on a predefined set
of these categories.
This is non-generative, as it's a classification task.
On the other hand, with large language models, these models choose their own open-ended labels
and are not limited to a predefined list.
You may recall this is like when you asked a model to identify all the sports that were
mentioned in a discussion forum.
So this is generative.
How about qualitative scoring?
If you have a model just give a number, a score from 0 to 10, to evaluate a debate speech, for instance, or an essay, this is non-generative.
What you saw in this course, when the model not only outputs a number, but also outputs criteria for evaluation and explanations for the scores it gives, this is generative.
So what I hope you see here is that before the arrival of powerful generative models,
a more limited version of some of these tasks could be performed by non-generative models.
It's also helpful to keep in mind that there are also benefits of using non-generative models
when you want to more clearly control what kind of output the model produces.
For example, sometimes the output of a model might be sent as the input to other software,
and that regular software expects specific inputs.
Sometimes people also prompt chatbots to encourage the outputs to be limited to a predefined set of outputs as well.
For example, they may prompt the model to give a single word answer, only yes or no, and do not provide additional explanations.
So in a way, this is prompting a generative model to try and behave in the same way as a non-generative model.
So what kinds of models are generative?
You've seen large language models, which are generative and produce text.
You also saw a little bit about diffusion models, which are primarily used to generate images.
There's also another category of models that were actually really popular for generating images just a few years ago,
called generative adversarial networks.
But most of the latest image generation models that have become popular lately are diffusion models.
Some examples include Stable Diffusion by Stability AI,
DAL-A3 by OpenAI, and EMU, which you saw in this course as Imagine by Meta-AI.
Large language models are actually based on a type of neural network called the transformer,
and you'll also hear that it's called the transformer architecture. Transformers are
part of a broader category of models called sequence models. Sequence models are designed
to be able to handle sequential data. For example, a piece of text in human language is sequential data
because the order of the words matter, and we process the words in order, for instance,
from left to right. Another example is DNA or RNA sequences, genomic data. Again, the order of these
letters, which are actually called nucleotides, matters in determining what kinds of proteins
these sequences are ultimately coding for. And there's also time series data, such as weather
or temperature over time, or stock data over time. There are different categories of sequence models
that have been designed to handle sequential data. One collection of models are called
recurrent neural networks. The way recurrent neural networks process sequential data is one
at a time. So if it's given a sequence of words, it first takes in the first word, then the second
word, the third word, and the fourth word, and then its task is to try and predict the next word
after that. So it processes the input sequence in series, one at a time. In contrast, a newer
sequence model that was developed by researchers at Google in 2017 is the transformer. If given a
piece of text like this, the transformer model can actually take in many of the words all at the same
time with an understanding of the order in which those words appeared in the original text. And
based on these inputs, it produces an output, such as the next word. So a major difference between
these two is that with a recurrent neural network, it processes the input sequence in series. In
contrast, the transformer model is able to process the input text in parallel, which makes it much
faster and also in practice makes it better able to handle long sequences. Another word you may
come across is the term foundation model. Let's first look at models that are not foundation
models. These are task-specific models. If you have a translation model, it takes an input piece
of text and assumes that its job is to translate that piece of text, not to do something else with
it. If you have a summarization model and you give it a piece of text, it knows that it's going to
try to summarize that piece of text and not do anything else with it. If you have a sentiment
analysis model and you give it a piece of text, such as a product review, then this model knows
that it's going to predict a number and not do something else, like try to summarize or translate.
So for every one model, it performs one specific task.
In contrast, let's look at a foundation model.
A large language model is an example of a foundation model.
If you give it a piece of text, as well as the instruction to translate to French, then
it will perform a translation task.
If you give that same model a movie script with the instruction to summarize that script,
then it will perform the summarization task.
If you give it a prompt to predict the rating of some product review, for example, between
one and five stars, then it will perform that task and output a star rating. So with one foundation
model, it can actually generalize to many tasks if prompted with some hints as to the task that you
want it to perform. And here's a brief look at how foundation models are trained. Again, let's take a
look at task-specific models to see how training foundation models is different. With a task-specific
model, it's given training data with input features and labels that are specific to the task that is
asked to learn. In this case, it is asked to take some product review and output a number that the
reviewer might have given based on the text of their review. So a task-specific model is being
given inputs and correct outputs that define how to perform a specific task, in this case,
sentiment analysis on a piece of text. In contrast with foundation models, they're just fed any piece
of text and asked to predict the next word, and the label in this case is the actual word that
in a textbook or online article that is being used for training. For example, with the text
twinkle twinkle little star, the input could be twinkle twinkle little, and then the label or the
correct output would be star. And the model might still be training, and so it might output its best
guess, which might be llama, for instance. Similarly, with a piece of text that says
happy birthday to you, the feature or input for the foundation model could be happy birthday to,
and the label that defines the correct answer would be you. The model will try its best guess,
for example it might say happy birthday to me, but the labels will be used to help the model learn.
So in the case of a large language model, the task that it's learning to perform is to predict the
next word, which you recall is officially called language modeling. And the key point here is that
the foundation model is not being explicitly trained to perform any other specific tasks,
such as translation or summarization or sentiment analysis.
And the reason why predicting the next word is a useful task
is that this allows the foundation model to take in a lot more data for training.
With other task-specific models, you would need humans to create the labels in the training data.
In contrast, when you're predicting the next word in a document,
then those labels already exist because each label is just the next word and piece of text.
So when these models have a lot more data that can be used for training, even though they're just predicting the next word,
these models are also learning about human language when they're being trained on so much text data.
And this allows foundation models to develop the ability to perform other useful tasks,
such as translation, summarization, sentiment analysis, and more,
even though they were not specifically trained to perform those tasks.
And so that's what a foundation model is.
It's a model that can learn broadly about a particular type of data, such as human language,
so that it can develop on its own the ability to perform useful tasks to process that data,
in this case, human language.
This task of learning from predicting the next word and a lot of text data is part of a training
process that includes pre-training followed by fine-tuning.
So a pre-trained model is also called a base model, and it has learned to predict the next
word given some input text.
This means that if you were to try and get the base model to perform a task that's useful to you,
you would need to phrase it in a way so that the useful outcome that you're looking for
would be the next word in that sentence. For instance, if I wanted it to recommend some nice
places to go on vacation, for a base model, I could try to give it a prompt such as,
a city I want to visit for a vacation is. Notice that this text is formatted as an
incomplete sentence. The base model may try to predict the next couple of words,
such as Paris, China, or Colorado. This is why it's called a completion because it's trying to
complete an incomplete sentence. To make it easier to use these models, they then go through an
additional training step to learn how to follow instructions. This is called instruction tuning,
and it gives the model more curated examples where the inputs look like this, suggest some dessert
options. Notice that this is formatted as an instruction, some task you're asking the model
to perform. While it's still learning, the model may initially try to complete an incomplete
sentence. So its completion might look like this. Suggest some appetizers. For instruction tuning,
the training data also includes examples of ideal completions, such as I recommend ice cream cake.
So this is formatted as a response to an instruction. And I'm simplifying the training
process a lot here, but you can have some performance measure and an optimizer update
the model so that it can learn. So after instruction tuning, you'll get an instruction tuned model,
which is what most of us are used to when we access a chatbot. If you give it an instruction,
such as, suggest a vacation itinerary, it will understand that this is an instruction,
an output text that is meant to satisfy that request, such as, I recommend Paris to China to
Colorado. You've heard of ChatGPT and may have heard that the underlying model created by OpenAI
is called GPT. But what does GPT stand for? Now, just for fun, you might be able to figure this out
if you rewind a little bit and look at all the text that was colored in green in the past couple
of slides. The G in GPT stands for generative because it can generate outputs that are new
sequences of text that could be responses to open-ended questions or requests. The P stands
for pre-trained. It's a foundation model that was pre-trained on a large amount of text data so that
it would have the ability to generalize to many tasks beyond just predicting the next word. And T
stands for transformer because the model design is based on the transformer architecture, a kind of
sequence model. So there you go. That's GPT. Next up, we'll go through more vocabulary words
that you might hear when you're learning about AI.
Bye.