In this course, you've downloaded some models which have been compressed enough that they can
actually fit on a personal computer. You may hear about different kinds of compression. One method
is called quantization. Here's a brief conceptual description of quantization. Recall that models
have parameters, and in the case of neural networks, these are called weights. And these
parameters store the learning and knowledge that a model gains when it's trained with data. You may
recall that these parameters are really just numbers, and in computers, numbers like decimal
points are typically stored as binary numbers with 32 bits. A bit is either a 0 or a 1, and on a
computer, a bit takes up a little bit of physical space on the computer hardware, but it adds up
when you have a lot of parameters. Quantization takes those parameters and stores them into a
smaller amount of space, such as 16 bits or even 8 bits. When you take a model that has billions
of parameters and convert its parameters from taking up 32 bits of space to 16 bits or 8 bits,
you allow the model to take up less space and therefore compress the model. In this case,
you're quantizing the model. Another method of compression is called distillation. At a
level is taking the original model and getting it to teach a smaller model to produce outputs that
are just like the original model. So what you can do is run inference on the original model, give it
inputs, and then save its outputs. For example, here's a riddle. In Spain, I call myself fiery
long neck. What am I? The model may output the Spanish word llamas, and you may recall this from
the translation lectures in the course. With the smaller model, you give it that same input, and it
give some output, which may not be the same, but now it has a label to compare to, which
is the output from the original big model. And so you can effectively train this smaller
model to behave similarly to that larger model. Yet another method of compression is called
pruning. This is similar to the concept of cutting leaves off of a bush or a tree. Remember
that the parameters of the models are just numbers. After a model is trained, you can
find out which of these parameters are actually more important or less important to the performance
of the model. The parameters that don't seem to make a big difference in how the model performs
can be set to zero in order to effectively deactivate them. This also saves space because
to store the number zero, you don't actually need to take up 32 bits for every parameter that you
know will always be zero. Another term you'll hear a lot about in the news is GPU. Every computer has
something called a CPU, a central processing unit. And this actually runs the computer,
kind of like the brain of the computer. And computers can also have an added piece of hardware
called a GPU, a graphics processing unit. It's really good at performing math operations
in parallel. So GPUs are really good for producing graphics, which is why they were initially used
for running video games on computers. And because machine learning training is actually a lot of
multiplication and addition, GPUs make it possible to perform machine learning training of models
as well as inference. So when a CPU picks up a task that requires a lot of math operations,
it can delegate that task to the GPU because the GPU can perform that task much faster and at a
higher volume. A hot topic among businesses that wish to make use of large language models is
called retrieval augmented generation. Let's first talk about some issues that led to the need for
retrieval augmented generation. Recall that large language models can hallucinate. For example,
you can ask it about yourself and it might make up something that's not true, even though it would
be lovely if it were true. Another issue for businesses is that employees at a company may
want to ask questions about the company's internal documents and processes. A large language model
that's trained on public data would not have been trained on this private company information.
For example, an employee at a company may want to ask how to operate one of the company's products.
A large language model would not be able to give a very specific answer about it.
Also recall that any chatbot has a context window that is limited to how much text you can give the model for any single prompt.
So you can't just give a chatbot all the documents to let it sort through them.
There's just not enough space.
Now there are models that can take in a lot of text at one time,
But an LLM would probably still perform better if you gave it the text that is most relevant to the task.
Otherwise, it's just TMI, or too much information.
So there's a need to find relevant documents and retrieve the relevant parts of those documents
to help a large language model answer these kinds of questions.
Here's a brief look at how retrieval augmented generation works.
You have a large language model, and you also have something called a vector database.
When you see the word vector, you can just think a long list of numbers, and you'll see why it's
called a vector database in a bit. If you ask a large language model a question, like who is
Eddie Xu, before the large language model answers, it first goes to a vector database, which has
stored a bunch of information about that particular topic that you're likely to ask about. This vector
database does a similarity search. This means that it converts the query into a list of numbers.
Similarity search can apply to text as well.
You may call from the lecture on similarity search that this list of numbers hold some
descriptive meaning about the object that is describing, and is called an embedding.
The vector database may have stored some relevant documents, such as a resume or dating profile.
These documents have been broken up into smaller chunks of text,
which also have embeddings calculated for them.
So the vector database finds chunks of text that are similar to the query based on those embeddings,
and might be relevant to answering that query. This retrieved text might look like these pieces
of text here. This text is then sent to the LLM so that the model is able to answer the questions
based on the retrieved text. The act of retrieving information that can be considered a source of
truth to help a model answer a question truthfully is called grounding the model, as in grounding
the model in facts or factual information. Yet another approach to giving large language models
domain-specific information is fine-tuning. You heard about instruction tuning earlier,
and more generally, fine-tuning is training a model on additional data to give it knowledge
about a specific subject area, or also to modify its behavior in other ways,
such as changing its tone or wording, or training it to handle sensitive topics safely. Normally,
you start with the pre-trained model, also called a base model. It goes through an additional
training process called fine-tuning, and the result is a fine-tuned model. So let's look at
this in more detail. The base model was trained on a huge dataset of unlabeled text. If asked a
domain-specific question, it won't know the answer. So you send the model through a fine-tuning process.
For this model, you give it curated labeled data. For instance, for a given input like this,
your training data also has examples of correct output, such as this or this. So you send this
the model, it outputs something that probably isn't quite right yet. And I'm simplifying the
next few steps a bit, but you can send the model's outputs and the labels, the examples of the correct
acceptable outputs, to a performance measure which an optimizer uses to update the model's parameters.
After you've done fine-tuning with this domain-specific dataset, you get a fine-tuned model.
So now, when you ask it domain-specific questions like this, it will output some useful information
that it learned from the fine-tuning process. Another word you may hear lately in the news about
AI are agents. People are still deciding what is the actual definition of an agent, but generally
they appear to be attempts at making applications that can make decisions and take actions
independently without needing much supervision from people. So far, agents are large language models
that are wrapped in additional code to make them so-called agents. And here are some properties of
agents. One is reflection, which you may recall from this course. Instead of having a user ask
the large language model if they're sure, or asking the LLM to review their own work, an agent already
has this built in, so that it will ask itself, am I sure? Or, let me review my work. Another feature
of agents is tool use, which you might recall from this course. It's the ability to take actions
beyond just outputting text, and some examples would be calling a web search or opening up a
calendar, and it could potentially be any other software application. Another aspect of agents is
planning, or the ability to think through a multi-step process. For instance, an agent that plays the
role of a travel agent might be able to think through the steps that it might take when it's
helping a customer with their vacation plans. For instance, first get a customer's vacation
preferences, then search for possible destinations that match those preferences, then search for
airline flights, and then book those flights. The idea is that an agent would first plan out a
process and then follow through on that multi-step process. And another aspect of agents is
collaboration. You saw a little bit of this in the chatbot to chatbot collaboration part of the
course, where you were an intermediary between one large language model who was the writer and
another large language model who was the editor. When you wrap each of these large language models
with code to make them more autonomous or to make them agents, so to speak, then the two can
collaborate fairly autonomously and you can sort of step back a little bit and maybe have a snack.
And so you might hear this being referred to as multi-AI agents.
So that was a lot of information.
You can sort of treat this more as a reference for you to look back on when you're reading
articles and doing your own learning.
And if you would like a more thorough explanation of any of these topics in an upcoming course,
then please feel free to let us know in the review comments.
Next, before we move on to the open-ended project, there's an optional discussion about
skill stacking, which is how you can approach thinking about how you can combine your skills
in a way to make you stand out. I'll see you in the next video or in the open-ended project.