If you try to be good at one thing, it might be really hard.
But what if you're pretty good at two things or maybe even three things?
Let's take a look at skill stacking and how you can use that to your advantage.
At some point in your life, you may have had some well-intentioned person tell you
to drop your hobbies so that you can focus on skills that will help you get a real job.
For example, you may have an interest in baking or sports or gardening.
Perhaps you have an interest in acting, telling jokes, or maybe writing short stories.
Maybe you really like playing music, painting, or singing.
Maybe you like dancing or fitness and health.
Maybe you're really into making pictures or making fun videos.
And the so-called professional skills you may also be trying to grow might be things like
math or coding, some other business-related skills, maybe medicine or healthcare, maybe
some of the sciences like physics, chemistry, or biology.
Maybe you're studying to be a journalist or marketing.
maybe working in hospitality and tourism, maybe you're studying to be a teacher. Sometimes you
may feel the pressure either from other people or from yourself to drop your hobbies so that you can
focus on your career. But maybe there's a way you can find some way to integrate your hobbies into
your career. Let's learn a little bit about skill stacking to see how this might work. You may have
many skills that you already have or are in the process of developing. It's kind of like having
several different kinds of utensils like spoons, forks, knives, chopsticks available to you when
you're ready to eat a meal. And depending on what kind of meal you might have today, certain tools or
utensils might be better to allow you to make the most of that meal. The idea behind skill stacking
is that instead of trying to be really really good at one skill, you might actually stand out more
if you're pretty good at a unique combination of two or more skills. So you could drop your hobbies
and try to be really, really good at one thing, like pursuing your skills in medicine.
And another path you might take is to combine a couple skills, including medicine, dance,
maybe your interest in video editing.
For instance, maybe you apply your understanding of dance to specialize in physical therapy
or fitness training for other dancers.
And maybe you take your hobby of editing videos to help you create fun videos on social media
to help educate others about fitness and health tips that can help dancers.
And you can find your own combination of hobbies and skills that you can apply towards a career.
One way you can think about how your combination of skills really sets you apart is by thinking
about how each of your skills fits in on a spectrum of technical or creative skills.
These aren't the only two ways that you can group your set of skills, but generally,
you can stand out if you have a mixture of both technical and creative skills.
So instead of dropping your hobbies to focus on your day job, you can think about how you
can apply your hobby to your day job. For instance, maybe you're really into photography and your day
job is a zoologist at a wildlife reserve. So perhaps you can apply your photography skills
to create a picture book about the animals that you're working with. Or maybe you're an avid dancer
and also a videographer. So you can apply your understanding of dance when you're filming and
editing videos for other people's dance performances. Maybe you're really good with editing and animating
videos and you can apply this to your job in marketing by creating fun marketing videos.
Maybe you're an artist and also learned coding, so you can apply this to your job as a video game
designer. Maybe you enjoy creative writing and you're also a computer programmer and you can
apply this to your work as a technical writer. Maybe you like telling jokes and doing stand-up
comedy, so in your day job as a teacher, you add in a few jokes to help your students stay awake.
Maybe they like your jokes so much that when you do a stand-up routine, they all come and watch
and laugh at your jokes. Anything's possible, right? Coming up next, you'll get to combine,
or maybe even stack, a couple of the skills that you've learned in this course
to help you with some of your everyday personal or work tasks. The Open-Ended Project is next.