Pretty cool, huh? Welcome to the future. You've now completed this course. There's just one
more thing I'd like you to do. Take both hands out like this, wiggle your fingers, and give
Give yourself a round of applause for completing this segment of your AI journey.
I hope you enjoyed the ride.
Bye now!
I actually didn't know how to end this.
And then maybe one with my hands out.
Congra...
Sorry.
Okay.
And then you'll probably need to cut me because I don't remember this.
And then pat yourself on the back and congratulate yourself.
Oh, I should have looked at that camera.
to congratulate yourself. Sorry. What if you computed... Oh, is someone gonna throw the ball
to me? Or am I gonna toss you one? Oh yes, could you toss me one? So instead of playing catch to
yourself, I'm just gonna toss it to you? Yeah, yeah. Does this require intelligence? Sorry.
Some tasks are harder. So should I pick it up sooner maybe? Is this a cake? Cheesecake. That
Sorry.
It just smells so good.
Let's take a closer look.
Oh, it smells so good.
Sorry.
Object detection.
I hope my brain is...
Okay.
Sorry, I moved.
It's up here.
Sorry.
I let the cat out of the bag.
It didn't.
Okay, yay, salad.
Okay, if you baked a cake, okay.
You may have at one point tried to discoo-
Oh my gosh, that was a bad thing, okay.
- Yeah, that's good.
- Welcome to the future.
You've now owned.
- No worries.
- Like, yeah, look that way.
Oh, this is crazy.
I think we're going to need to take like four or five more takes of this.
Okay, thanks.
All right.
Got it.
Mm-hmm.